<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools"
    tools:ignore="MissingTranslation"
    <string name="app_name">Remember Allah</string>
    <string name="share">Share</string>
    <string name="volume_level">Notification Volume Level</string>
    <string name="mute_when_ringer_mute">Mute Notification If Device Is In Silent Mode</string>
    <string name="morningThikr">Morning Rememberance</string>
    <string name="nightThikr">Evening Rememberance</string>
    <string name="now_playing">Now playing</string>
    <string name="morningThikrSettings">Morning Rememberance Settings</string>
    <string name="nightThikrSettings">Evening rememberance Settings</string>
    <string name="RemindMe">Remind Me Of Allah</string>
    <string name="Settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="play_all">Play all</string>
    <string name="remindMeMorningThikr">Remind Me Of Morning rememberance</string>
    <string name="remindMeNightThikr">Remind Me Of Evening rememberance</string>
    <string name="changeReminderTime">Modify Reminder Time</string>
    <string name="RemindMeSettings">Auto Reminders Settings</string>
    <string name="general_thikr_reminder_type">Method Of Allah\'s Remembrance</string>
    <string name="RemindMeEvery">Remind Me Of Allah Every</string>
    <string name="chooseDailyThikr">Choose a Dua\'a For Daily Reminders</string>
    <string name="RemindmeThroughTheDay">Remind Me Of Allah Throughout Day</string>
    <string name="thanksforupgrade">We thank you for supporting developer by making the donation. If you have any recommendation, please email us or leave feedback on Google\'s Play Store</string>
    <string name="support_us_request">Please support the developer my clicking on interesting ads every now and then and by making dua\'a for me.</string>
    <string name="support_us">Support Us</string>
    <string name="whatsnew">&#8226; We recommend opening settings to change any of the default settings.\n&#8226; Clicking on ads once, makes ads disappear for 7 days.
\n&#8226; Making donation makes the app ads free forever.
\n&#8226; May Allah guide you to his remembrance and worship. Please don\'t forget us from your prayers.</string>
    <string name="contactUs">Contact Us</string>
    <string name="email_Us">Email Us</string>
    <string name="email_subject">App Recommendations</string>
    <string name="quiet_time">Time To Stop Reminders</string>
    <string name="quiet_time_choice">Stop Audio Reminders During This Time</string>
    <string name="quiet_time_start">No Reminders Time Starts On:</string>
    <string name="quiet_time_end">No Reminders Time Ends On</string>
    <string name="rate_message">If you have any good or bad experience using our app, please give us a minute of your time to give us that feedback so that we can improve this app God willing. Also, please support us by clicking on interesting ads every now and then. Thank you.</string>
    <string name="rate">Rate App</string>
    <string name="remind_later">Remind Me Again</string>
    <string name="dont_rate">I do not want to rate app</string>
    <string name="athan">Athan</string>
    <string name="sunrise">Sunrise</string>
    <string name="sunset">Sunset</string>
    <string name="prayer1">Fajr Prayer</string>
    <string name="prayer2">Duhr Prayer</string>
    <string name="prayer3">Asr Prayer</string>
    <string name="prayer4">Maghrib Prayer</string>
    <string name="prayer5">Isha Prayer</string>
    <string name="open_settings">Open settings</string>
    <string name="my_athkar">My Dua\'a</string>
    <string name="cancel">Cancel</string>
    <string name="add_thikr">Add Supplication</string>
    <string name="add_thikr_hint">Supplication Text Here</string>
    <string name="one_thikr_warning">At least one of the built-in supplication must be enabled</string>

    <string name="notification_sound_and_text">Audio And Visual Reminder</string>
    <string name="notification_sound_only">Audio Reminder Only</string>
    <string name="notification_text_only">Visual Reminder Only</string>
    <string name="play_athkar_at_notification_time">Play Supplications Audio At Time Of Reminder</string>
    <string name="one_minute">1 minute</string>
    <string name="five_minutes">5 minutes</string>
    <string name="ten_minutes">10 minutes</string>
    <string name="fifteen_minutes">15 minutes</string>
    <string name="thirty_minutes">30 minutes</string>
    <string name="one_hour">1 hour</string>
    <string name="two_hours">2 hours</string>
    <string name="three_hours">3 hours</string>
    <string name="four_hours">4 hours</string>
    <string name="five_hours">5 hours</string>
    <string name="six_hours">6 hours</string>
    <string name="seven_hours">7 hours</string>
    <string name="eight_hours">8 hours</string>
    <string name="nine_hours">9 hours</string>
    <string name="ten_hours">10 hours</string>
    <string name="eleven_hours">11 hours</string>
    <string name="twelve_hours">12 hours</string>

    <string name="thikr1">Glory be to Allah\n(Subhan Allah)</string>
    <string name="thikr2">Praise be to Allah\n(Alhamdulillah)</string>
    <string name="thikr3">There is no god but Allah\n(La ilaha illallah )</string>
    <string name="thikr4">God is the Greatest\n(Allahu Akbar)</string>
    <string name="thikr5">There is neither strength nor power except with Allah\n(La Haula wala Quwwata il-la bil-lah)</string>
    <string name="thikr6">O Allah, bless prophet Muhammad.\n(Allahumma sallee wasalim ala nabiena muhammad)</string>
    <string name="thikr7">I ask for forgiveness\n(Astaghfirul lah )</string>

    <string name="thikr_kursi"><b><i>There is no god but He, The Living, the Everlasting,
Slumber seizes Him not, neither sleep, To Him belongs all that is in the heavens and the earth. Who is there that can intercede with His, except by His leave?
He knows what lies before them and what is after them, And they comprehend not anything of His Knowledge save as He wills. His throne comprises the heavens and the earth, The preserving of them fatigues Him not, And He is the All-High, All-Glorious.</i></b>\n\n(Allahu la ilaha illa Huwa, Al-Haiyul-Qaiyum La ta\'khudhuhu sinatun wa la nawm, lahu ma fis-samawati wa ma fil-\'ard Man dhal-ladhi yashfa\'u \'indahu illa bi-idhnihi Ya\'lamu ma baina aidihim wa ma khalfahum, wa la yuhituna bi shai\'im-min \'ilmihi illa bima sha\'a Wasi\'a kursiyuhus-samawati wal ard, wa la ya\'uduhu hifdhuhuma Wa Huwal \'Aliyul-Adheem)</string>
    <string name="thikr_iklhlas"><b><i>Say: He is Allah, the One and Only; Allah, the Eternal, Absolute; He begetteth not, nor is He begotten; And there is none like unto Him.</i></b>\n\n(Qul huwal laahu ahad. Allah hus-samad. Lam yalid wa lam yoolad. Wa lam yakul-lahu kufuwan ahad)</string>
    <string name="thikr_alfalak"><b><i>Say: I seek refuge with the Lord of the Dawn. From the mischief of created things; From the mischief of Darkness as it overspreads; From the mischief of those who practice secret arts; And from the mischief of the envious one as he practices envy.</i></b>\n\n(Qul a\'uzoo bi rabbil-falaq. Min sharri ma khalaq. Wa min sharri ghasiqin iza waqab. Wa min sharrin-naffaa-thaati fil \'uqad. Wa min shar ri haasidin iza hasad.</string>
    <string name="thikr_alnas"><b><i>Say: I seek refuge with the Lord and Cherisher of Mankind, The King (or Ruler) of Mankind, The Allah (for judge) of Mankind,From the mischief of the Whisperer (of Evil), who withdraws (after his whisper),(The same) who whispers into the hearts of Mankind, Among Jinns and among men.</i></b>\n\nQul a\'uzu birabbin naas. Malikin naas. Ilaahin naas. Min sharril was waasil khannaas. Al lazee yuwas wisu fee sudoorin naas. Minal jinnati wan naas</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr1"><b><i>We have reached the morning and at this very time unto Allah belongs all sovereignty, and all praise is for Allah. None has the right to be worshiped except Allah, alone, without partner, to Him belongs all sovereignty and praise and He is over all things omnipotent. My Lord, I ask You for the good of this day and the good of what follows it and I take refuge in You from the evil of this day and the evil of what follows it. My Lord, I take refuge in You from laziness and senility. My Lord, I take refuge in You from torment in the Fire and punishment in the grave.</i></b>\n\n(Asbahna wa-asbahal-mulku lillah walhamdu lillah la ilaha illal-lah, wahdahu la shareeka lah, lahul-mulku walahul-hamd, wahuwa AAala kulli shayin qadeer, rabbi as-aluka khayra ma fee hatha-alyawmi, wakhayra ma baAAdaho, wa-aAAoothu bika min sharri hatha-alyawmi, washarri ma baAAdaho, rabbi aAAoothu bika minal-kasal, wasoo-il kibar, rabbi aAAoothu bika min AAathabin fin-nar, waAAathabin fil-qabr.)</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr2"><b><i>O Allah, by your leave we have reached the morning and by Your leave we have reached the evening, by Your leave we live and die and unto You is our resurrection.</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma bika asbahna wabika amsayna, wabika nahya ,wabika namootu wa-ilaykan-nushoor)</string>
    <string name="thikr_istighfar"><b><i>O Allah, You are my Lord, none has the right to be worshipped except You, You created me and I am Your servant and I abide to Your covenant and promise as best I can, I take refuge in You from the evil of which I have committed. I acknowledge Your favour upon me and I acknowledge my sin, so forgive me, for verily none can forgive sin except You.</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma anta rabbee la ilaha illa ant, khalaqtanee wa-ana AAabduk, wa-ana AAala AAahdika wawaAAdika mas-tataAAt, aAAoothu bika min sharri ma sanaAAt, aboo-o laka biniAAmatika AAalay, wa-aboo-o bithanbee, faghfir lee fa-innahu la yaghfiruth-thunooba illa ant)</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr3"><b><i>O Allah, verily I have reached the morning and call on You, the bearers of Your throne, Your angles, and all of Your creation to witness that You are Allah, none has the right to be worshiped except You, alone, without partner and that Muhammad is Your Servant and Messenger. (4 times).</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma innee asbahtu oshhiduk, wa-oshhidu hamalata AAarshik, wamala-ikatak, wajameeAAa khalqik, annaka antal-lahu la ilaha illa ant, wahdaka la shareeka lak, wa-anna Muhammadan AAabduka warasooluk (4 times). )</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr4"><b><i>O Allah, what blessing I or any of Your creation have risen upon, is from You alone, without partner, so for You is all praise and unto You all thanks.</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma ma asbaha bee min niAAmatin, aw bi-ahadin min khalqik, faminka wahdaka la shareeka lak, falakal-hamdu walakash-shukr)</string>
    <string name="thikr_afani"><b><i>O Allah, grant my body health, O Allah, grant my hearing health, O Allah, grant my sight health. None has the right to be worshipped except You. (3 times)</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma AAafinee fee badanee, allahumma AAafinee fee samAAee, allahumma AAafinee fee basaree, la ilaha illa ant.(3 times))</string>
    <string name="thikr_hasbi"><b><i>Allah is Sufficient for me, none has the right to be worshipped except Him, upon Him I rely and He is Lord of the exalted throne. (7 times)</i></b>\n\n(Hasbiyal-lahu la ilaha illa huwa, AAalayhi tawakkalt, wahuwa rabbul-AAarshil-AAatheem  (7 times) )</string>
    <string name="thikr_alafo"><b><i>O Allah, I ask You for pardon and well-being in this life and the next. O Allah, I ask You for pardon and well-being in my religious and worldly affairs, and my family and my wealth. O Allah, veil my weaknesses and set at ease my dismay. O Allah, preserve me from the front and from behind and on my right and on my left and from above, and I take refuge with You lest I be swallowed up by the earth.</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma innee as-alukal-AAafwa walAAafiyah, fid-dunya wal-akhirah, allahumma innee as-alukal-AAafwa walAAafiyah fee deenee, wadunyaya wa-ahlee, wamalee, allahummas-tur AAawratee, wa-amin rawAAatee, allahummah-fathnee min bayni yaday, wamin khalfee, waAAan yameenee, waAAan shimalee, wamin fawqee, wa-aAAoothu biAAathamatika an oghtala min tahtee.)</string>
    <string name="thikr_alem"><b><i>O Allah, Knower of the unseen and the seen, Creator of the heavens and the Earth, Lord and Sovereign of all things, I bear witness that none has the right to be worshiped except You. I take refuge in You from the evil of my soul and from the evil and shirk of the devil, and from committing wrong against my soul or bringing such upon another Muslim.</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma AAalimal-ghaybi washshahadah, fatiras-samawati wal-ard, rabba kulli shayin wamaleekah, ashhadu an la ilaha illa ant, aAAoothu bika min sharri nafsee wamin sharrish-shaytani washirkih, waan aqtarifa AAala nafsee soo-an aw ajurrahu ila muslim)</string>
    <string name="thikr_wikaya"><b><i>In the name of Allah with whose name nothing is harmed on earth nor in the heavens and He is The All-Seeing, The All-Knowing(3 times)</i></b>\n\n(Bismil-lahil-lathee la yadurru maAAas-mihi shay-on fil-ardi wala fis-sama-i wahuwas-sameeAAul-AAaleem (3 times) )</string>
    <string name="thikr_istighatha"><b><i>O Ever Living, O Self-Subsisting and Supporter of all, by Your mercy I seek assistance, rectify for me all of my affairs and do not leave me to myself, even for the blink of an eye.</i></b>\n\n(Ya hayyu ya qayyoom, birahmatika astagheeth, aslih lee sha/nee kullah, wala takilnee ila nafsee tarfata AAayn.)</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr5"><b><i>We have reached the morning and at this very time all sovereignty belongs to Allah, Lord of the worlds. O Allah, I ask You for the good of this day, its triumphs and its victories, its light and its blessings and its guidance, and I take refuge in You from the evil of this day and the evil that follows it.</i></b>\n\n(Asbahna wa-asbahal-mulku lillahi rabbil-AAalameen, allahumma innee as-aluka khayra hathal-yawm, fat-hahu, wanasrahu, wanoorahu, wabarakatahu, wahudahu, wa-aAAoothu bika min sharri ma feehi, washarri ma baAAdah.)</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr6"><b><i>Our morning-rise upon the fitrah (nature) of Islam, and the word of pure faith, and upon the religion of prophet Mohamed (Peace and Blessings of Allah be upon him) and the creed of prophet Ibrahim (Alayh Asalam), who was a Muslim of true faith and was not amongst who associate partners with Allah</i></b>\n\n(Asbahna ‘Ala Fitrat Al Islam Wa ‘Ala Kalimat Al Ikhlas, Wa ‘Ala Dini Nabyna Muhamadin(Sala Allahu ‘Alayhi Wa Salam) Wa ‘Ala Milati Ibraheem Hanifan Musliman Wa Ma Kana Minal Mushrikin)</string>
    <string name="thikr_subhan"><b><i>Allah is exalted with his praise, the number of His creatures and His pleasure, by the weight of His throne and the ink of His words (3 times)</i></b>\n\n(Subahana Allah Wa bi Hamdih, ‘Adada Khalqih, Wa Rida Nafsih Wa Zinata ‘Arshih Wa Midada Kalimateh) (3 times)</string>
    <string name="morning_thikr7"><b><i>O Allaah indeed I ask You for beneficial knowledge, and a good Halal provision, and actions which are accepted.</i></b>\n\n(Allaahumma innee assaluka ilman nafia, wa rizzqan tayyeebun, wa amalan mutaqabilan)</string>
    <string name="thikr_taoba"><b><i>I beg forgiveness from Allah and I turn to Him in repentance (3 times) )</i></b>\n\n(Astaghfiru Allah a\'atooob Elaih (3 times))</string>
    <string name="thikr_salah"><b><i>O Allah, bless prophet Muhammad (10 times).</i></b>\n\n(Allahumma sallee ala nabiena muhammad (10 times))</string>


    <string name="night_thikr1"><b><i>We have reached the evening and at this very time unto Allah belongs all sovereignty, and all praise is for Allah. None has the right to be worshiped except Allah, alone, without partner, to Him belongs all sovereignty and praise and He is over all things omnipotent. My Lord, I ask You for the good of this night and the good of what follows it and I take refuge in You from the evil of this night and the evil of what follows it. My Lord, I take refuge in You from laziness and senility. My Lord, I take refuge in You from torment in the Fire and punishment in the grave.</i></b>\n(Amsayna wa-amsal-mulku lillah walhamdu lillah la ilaha illal-lah, wahdahu la shareeka lah, lahul-mulku walahul-hamd, wahuwa AAala kulli shayin qadeer, rabbi as-aluka khayra ma fee hathihil-laylah, wakhayra ma baAAdaha, wa-aAAoothu bika min sharri hathihil-laylah, washarri ma baAAdaha, rabbi aAAoothu bika minal-kasal, wasoo-il kibar, rabbi aAAoothu bika min AAathabin fin-nar, waAAathabin fil-qabr.)</string>
    <string name="night_thikr2"><b><i>O Allah, by Your leave we have reached the evening and by Your leave we have reached the morning, by Your leave we live and die and unto You is our return.</i></b>\n(Allahumma bika amsayna, wabika asbahna, wabika nahya wabika namootu wa-ilayka-nushoor)</string>
    <string name="night_thikr3"><b><i>O Allah, verily I have reached the evening and call on You, the bearers of Your throne, Your angles, and all of Your creation to witness that You are Allah, none has the right to be worshiped except You, alone, without partner and that Muhammad is Your Servant and Messenger (4 times).</i></b>\n(Allahumma innee amsaytu oshhiduk, wa-oshhidu hamalata AAarshik, wamala-ikatak, wajameeAAa khalqik, annaka antal-lahu la ilaha illa ant, wahdaka la shareeka lak, wa-anna Muhammadan AAabduka warasooluk (4 times))</string>
    <string name="night_thikr4"><b><i>O Allah, what blessing I or any of Your creation have risen upon, is from You alone, without partner, so for You is all praise and unto You all thanks.</i></b>\n(Allahumma ma amsa bee min niAAmatin, aw bi-ahadin min khalqik, faminka wahdaka la shareeka lak, falakal-hamdu walakash-shukr)</string>
    <string name="night_thikr5"><b><i>I am pleased with Allah as a Lord, and Islam as a religion and Muhammad peace be upon to him as a Prophet (3 times).</i></b>\n(Radeetu billahi rabban wabil-islami deenan wabiMuhammadin nabiyya (3 times))</string>
    <string name="night_thikr6"><b><i>We have reached the evening and at this very time all sovereignty belongs to Allah, Lord of the worlds. O Allah, I ask You for the good of this day, its triumphs and its victories, its light and its blessings and its guidance, and I take refuge in You from the evil of this day and the evil that follows it.</i></b>\n(Amsayna wa-amsal-mulku lillahi rabbil-AAalameen, allahumma innee as-aluka khayra hathal-yawm, fat-hahu, wanasrahu, wanoorahu, wabarakatahu, wahudahu, wa-aAAoothu bika min sharri ma feehi, washarri ma baAAdah)</string>
    <string name="night_thikr7"><b><i>We have entered a new night upon the natural religion of Islam, the word of sincere devotion, the religion of our Prophet Muhammad (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him), and the faith of our father Ibrahim. He was upright (in worshipping Allah), and a Muslim. He was not of those who worship others besides Allah.</i></b>\n(Amsainaa \'alaa fitratil-\'Islaami wa \'alaa kalimatil-\'ikhlaasi, wa \'alaa deeni Nabiyyinaa Muhammadin (sallallaahu \'alayhi wa sallama), wa \'alaa millati \'abeenaa \'Ibraaheema, haneefan Musliman wa maa kaana minal-mushrikeen)</string>
    <string name="night_thikr8"><b><i>None has the right to be worshipped except Allah, alone, without partner, to Him belongs all sovereignty and praise, and He is over all things omnipotent (10 times).</i></b>\n(La ilaha illal-lah, wahdahu la shareeka lah, lahul-mulku walahul-hamd, wahuwa AAala kulli shay-in qadeer (10 times))</string>
    <string name="night_thikr9"><b><i>I take refuge in Allah’s perfect words from the evil He has created (3 times)</i></b>\n(aAAoothu bikalimatil-lahit-tammati min sharri ma khalaq (3 times))</string>
    <string name="language">Language</string>
    <string name="help_translate">Help Us Translate To Other Languages</string>
    <string name="share_text">I advise you to install this app called Remember Allah.\n\n It\'s a way to remember Allah throughout the day by providing you with notification reminders of Allah as well as audio reminders. I advise you to also share this message with other Muslims. It will benefit you with the ongoing reward of spreading it and it benefits them as well.\n\nAndroid: https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.HMSolutions.thikrallah  \n\nIphone: By a different developer but does same thing https://itunes.apple.com/app/id1004470625 \n</string>
    <string name="sadaqa">Spread Allah\'s Name</string>
    <string name="quranic_verses">Quran</string>
    <string name="kahfThikrSettings">Surat Alkahf Reminders Settings</string>
    <string name="remindMekahf">Remind Me Of Surat Alkahf on Fridays</string>
    <string name="kahf_reminder_type">Reminder Method</string>

    <string name="surat_alkahf_text">\n\nالْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ الَّذِي أَنزَلَ عَلَى عَبْدِهِ الْكِتَابَ وَلَمْ يَجْعَل لَّهُ عِوَجًا\n\n\n Alhamdu lillaahil lazeee anzala \'alaa \'abdihil kitaaba wa lam yaj\'al lahoo \'iwajaa\n\n Praise be to Allah Who hath sent to His Servant the Book, and hath allowed therein no Crookedness: (1)\n\nقَيِّمًا لِّيُنذِرَ بَأْسًا شَدِيدًا مِن لَّدُنْهُ وَيُبَشِّرَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ الَّذِينَ يَعْمَلُونَ الصَّالِحَاتِ أَنَّ لَهُمْ أَجْرًا حَسَنًا\n\n\n Qaiyimal liyunzira baasan shadeedam mil ladunhu wa yubashshiral mu\'mineenal lazeena ya\'maloonas saalihaati anna lahum ajran hasanaa\n\n  (He hath made it) Straight (and Clear), in order that He may warn (the godless) of a terrible Punishment from Him, and that He may give Glad Tidings to the Believers who work righteous deeds, that they shall have a goodly Reward. (2)\n\nمَاكِثِينَ فِيهِ أَبَدًا\n\n\n Maakiseena feehi abadaa\n\n  Wherein they shall remain forever: (3)\n\nوَيُنذِرَ الَّذِينَ قَالُوا اتَّخَذَ اللَّهُ وَلَدًا\n\n\n Wa yunziral lazeena qaalut takhazal laahu waladaa\n\n  Further that He may warn those (also) who say Allah hath begotten a son: (4)\n\nمَّا لَهُم بِهِ مِنْ عِلْمٍ وَلا لِآبَائِهِمْ كَبُرَتْ كَلِمَةً تَخْرُجُ مِنْ أَفْوَاهِهِمْ إِن يَقُولُونَ إِلاَّ كَذِبًا\n\n\n Maa lahum bihee min \'ilminw wa laa li aabaaa\'ihim; kaburat kalimatan takhruju min afwaahihim; iny yaqooloona illaa kazibaa\n\n  No knowledge have they of such a thing, nor had their fathers. It is a grievous thing that issues from their mouths as a saying. What they say is nothing but falsehood! (5)\n\nفَلَعَلَّكَ بَاخِعٌ نَّفْسَكَ عَلَى آثَارِهِمْ إِن لَّمْ يُؤْمِنُوا بِهَذَا الْحَدِيثِ أَسَفًا\n\n\n Fala\'allaka baakhi\'un nafsaka \'alaaa aasaarihim illam yu;minoo bihaazal hadeesi asafaa\n\n  Thou wouldst only perchance, fret thyself to death, following after them, in grief, if they believe not in this Message. (6)\n\nإِنَّا جَعَلْنَا مَا عَلَى الأَرْضِ زِينَةً لَّهَا لِنَبْلُوَهُمْ أَيُّهُمْ أَحْسَنُ عَمَلا\n\n\n Innaa ja\'alnaa ma \'alal ardi zeenatal lahaa linabluwahum ayyuhum ahsanu \'amalaa\n\n  That which is on earth We have made but as a glittering show for the earth, in order that We may test them, as to which of them are best in conduct. (7)\n\nوَإِنَّا لَجَاعِلُونَ مَا عَلَيْهَا صَعِيدًا جُرُزًا\n\n\n Wa innaa lajaa \'iloona maa \'alaihaa sa\'aeedan juruzaa\n\n  Verily what is on earth We shall make but as dust and dry soil (without growth or herbage). (8)\n\nأَمْ حَسِبْتَ أَنَّ أَصْحَابَ الْكَهْفِ وَالرَّقِيمِ كَانُوا مِنْ آيَاتِنَا عَجَبًا\n\n\n Am hasibta anna Ashaabal Kahfi war Raqeemi kaanoo min Aayaatinaa \'ajabaa\n\n  Or dost thou reflect that the Companions of the Cave and of the Inscription were wonders among Our Signs? (9)\n\nإِذْ أَوَى الْفِتْيَةُ إِلَى الْكَهْفِ فَقَالُوا رَبَّنَا آتِنَا مِن لَّدُنكَ رَحْمَةً وَهَيِّئْ لَنَا مِنْ أَمْرِنَا رَشَدًا\n\n\n Iz awal fityatu ilal Kahfi faqaaloo Rabbanaaa aatinaa mil ladunka rahmatanw wa haiyi\' lanaa min amrinaa rashadaa\n\n  Behold, the youths betook themselves to the Cave: they said Our Lord! Bestow on us Mercy from Thyself, and dispose of our affair for us in the right way! (10)\n\nفَضَرَبْنَا عَلَى آذَانِهِمْ فِي الْكَهْفِ سِنِينَ عَدَدًا\n\n\n Fadarabnaa \'alaaa aazaanihim fil Kahfi seneena \'adadaa\n\n  Then We drew (a veil) over their ears, for a number of years, in the Cave, (so that they heard not): (11)\n\nثُمَّ بَعَثْنَاهُمْ لِنَعْلَمَ أَيُّ الْحِزْبَيْنِ أَحْصَى لِمَا لَبِثُوا أَمَدًا\n\n\n Summa ba\'asnaahum lina\'lama ayyul hizbaini ahsaa limaa labisooo amadaa\n\n  Then We roused them, in order to test which of the two parties was best at calculating the term of years they had tarried! (12)\n\nنَحْنُ نَقُصُّ عَلَيْكَ نَبَأَهُم بِالْحَقِّ إِنَّهُمْ فِتْيَةٌ آمَنُوا بِرَبِّهِمْ وَزِدْنَاهُمْ هُدًى\n\n\n Nahnu naqussu \'alaika naba ahum bilhaqq; innahum fityatun aamanoo bi Rabbihim wa zidnaahum hudaa\n\n  We relate to thee their story in truth: they were youths who believed in their Lord, and We advanced them in guidance: (13)\n\nوَرَبَطْنَا عَلَى قُلُوبِهِمْ إِذْ قَامُوا فَقَالُوا رَبُّنَا رَبُّ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالأَرْضِ لَن نَّدْعُوَ مِن دُونِهِ إِلَهًا لَقَدْ قُلْنَا إِذًا شَطَطًا\n\n\n Wa rabatnaa \'alaa quloo bihim iz qaamoo faqaaloo Rabbunaa Rabbus samaawaati wal ardi lan nad\'uwa min dooniheee ilaahal laqad qulnaaa izan shatataa\n\n  We gave strength to their hearts: behold, they stood up and said: Our Lord is the Lord of the heavens and of the earth: never shall we call upon any god other than Him: if we did; we should indeed have uttered an enormity! (14)\n\nهَؤُلاء قَوْمُنَا اتَّخَذُوا مِن دُونِهِ آلِهَةً لَّوْلا يَأْتُونَ عَلَيْهِم بِسُلْطَانٍ بَيِّنٍ فَمَنْ أَظْلَمُ مِمَّنِ افْتَرَى عَلَى اللَّهِ كَذِبًا\n\n\n Haaa\'ulaaa\'i qawmunat takhazoo min dooniheee aalihatal law laa yaatoona \'alaihim bisultaanim baiyin; faman azlamu mimmaniftaraa \'alal laahi kazibaa\n\n  These our people have taken for worship gods other than Him: why do they not bring forward an authority clear (and convincing) for what they do? Who doth more wrong than such as invent a falsehood against Allah? (15)\n\nوَإِذِ اعْتَزَلْتُمُوهُمْ وَمَا يَعْبُدُونَ إِلاَّ اللَّهَ فَأْوُوا إِلَى الْكَهْفِ يَنشُرْ لَكُمْ رَبُّكُم مِّن رَّحْمَتِه ويُهَيِّئْ لَكُم مِّنْ أَمْرِكُم مِّرْفَقًا\n\n\n Wa izi\'tazal tumoohum wa maa ya\'budoona illal laaha faawooo ilal kahfi yanshur lakum Rabbukum mir rahmatihee wa yuhaiyi\' lakum min amrikum mirfaqa\n\n  When ye turn away from them and the things they worship other than Allah betake yourselves to the Cave: your Lord will shower His mercies on you and dispose of your affair towards comfort and ease. (16)\n\nوَتَرَى الشَّمْسَ إِذَا طَلَعَت تَّزَاوَرُ عَن كَهْفِهِمْ ذَاتَ الْيَمِينِ وَإِذَا غَرَبَت تَّقْرِضُهُمْ ذَاتَ الشِّمَالِ وَهُمْ فِي فَجْوَةٍ مِّنْهُ ذَلِكَ مِنْ آيَاتِ اللَّهِ مَن يَهْدِ اللَّهُ فَهُوَ الْمُهْتَدِ وَمَن يُضْلِلْ فَلَن تَجِدَ لَهُ وَلِيًّا مُّرْشِدًا\n\n\n Wa tarash shamsa izaa tala\'at tazaawaru \'an kahfihim zaatal yameeni wa izaa gharabat taqriduhum zaatash shimaali wa hum fee fajwatim minh; zaalika min Aayaatillaah; mai yahdil laahu fahuwal muhtad, wa mai yudlil falan tajida lahoo waliyyam murshidaa\n\n  Thou wouldst have seen the sun, when it rose, declining to the right from their Cave, and when it set, turning away from them to the left while they lay in the open space in the midst of the Cave. Such are among the Signs of Allah: he whom Allah guides; but he whom Allah leaves to stray for him wilt thou find no protector to lead him to the Right Way. (17)\n\nوَتَحْسَبُهُمْ أَيْقَاظًا وَهُمْ رُقُودٌ وَنُقَلِّبُهُمْ ذَاتَ الْيَمِينِ وَذَاتَ الشِّمَالِ وَكَلْبُهُم بَاسِطٌ ذِرَاعَيْهِ بِالْوَصِيدِ لَوِ اطَّلَعْتَ عَلَيْهِمْ لَوَلَّيْتَ مِنْهُمْ فِرَارًا وَلَمُلِئْتَ مِنْهُمْ رُعْبًا\n\n\n Wa tahsabuhum ayqaazanw wa hum ruqood; wa nuqallibuhum zaatal yameeni wa zaatash shimaali wa kalbuhum baasitun ziraa\'ayhi bilwaseed; lawit tala\'ta \'alaihim la wallaita minhum firaaranw wa lamuli\'ta minhum rubaa\n\n  Thou wouldst have deemed them awake, whilst they were asleep, and We turned them on their right and their left sides: their dog stretching forth his two forelegs on the threshold: if thou hadst come up on to them, thou wouldst have certainly turned back from them in flight, and wouldst certainly have been filled with terror of them. (18)\n\nوَكَذَلِكَ بَعَثْنَاهُمْ لِيَتَسَاءَلُوا بَيْنَهُمْ قَالَ قَائِلٌ مِّنْهُمْ كَمْ لَبِثْتُمْ قَالُوا لَبِثْنَا يَوْمًا أَوْ بَعْضَ يَوْمٍ قَالُوا رَبُّكُمْ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا لَبِثْتُمْ فَابْعَثُوا أَحَدَكُم بِوَرِقِكُمْ هَذِهِ إِلَى الْمَدِينَةِ فَلْيَنظُرْ أَيُّهَا أَزْكَى طَعَامًا فَلْيَأْتِكُم بِرِزْقٍ مِّنْهُ وَلْيَتَلَطَّفْ وَلا يُشْعِرَنَّ بِكُمْ أَحَدًا\n\n\n Wa kazaalika ba\'asnaahum liyatasaaa\'aloo bainahum; qaala qaaa\'ilum minhum kam labistum qaaloo labisnaa yawman aw ba\'da yawm; qaaloo Rabbukum a\'almu bimaa labistum fab\'asooo ahadakum biwariqikum haazihee ilal madeenati falyanzur ayyuhaaa azkaa ta\'aaman falyaatikum birizqim minhu walyatalattaf wa laa yush\'iranna bikum ahadaa\n\n  Such (being their state), We raised them up (from sleep), that they might question each other. Said one of them How long have ye stayed (here)? They said We have stayed (perhaps) a day or part of a day. (At length) they (all) said Allah (alone) knows best how long ye have stayed here...Now send ye then one of you with this money of yours to the town: let him find out which is the best food (to be had) and bring some to you, that (ye may satisfy hunger therewith:) and let him behave with care and courtesy, and let him not inform anyone about you. (19)\n\nإِنَّهُمْ إِن يَظْهَرُوا عَلَيْكُمْ يَرْجُمُوكُمْ أَوْ يُعِيدُوكُمْ فِي مِلَّتِهِمْ وَلَن تُفْلِحُوا إِذًا أَبَدًا\n\n\n Innahum iny yazharoo \'alaikum yarjumookum aw yu\'eedookum fee millatihim wa lan tuflihooo izan abadaa\n\n  For if thy should come upon you, they would stone you or force you to return to their cult, and in that case ye would never attain prosperity. (20)\n\nوَكَذَلِكَ أَعْثَرْنَا عَلَيْهِمْ لِيَعْلَمُوا أَنَّ وَعْدَ اللَّهِ حَقٌّ وَأَنَّ السَّاعَةَ لا رَيْبَ فِيهَا إِذْ يَتَنَازَعُونَ بَيْنَهُمْ أَمْرَهُمْ فَقَالُوا ابْنُوا عَلَيْهِم بُنْيَانًا رَّبُّهُمْ أَعْلَمُ بِهِمْ قَالَ الَّذِينَ غَلَبُوا عَلَى أَمْرِهِمْ لَنَتَّخِذَنَّ عَلَيْهِم مَّسْجِدًا\n\n\n Wa kazaalika a\'sarnaa \'alaihim liya\'lamooo anna wa\'dal laahi haqqunw wa annas Saa\'ata laa raiba feehaa iz yatanaaza\'oona bainahum amrahum faqaalub noo \'alaihim bunyaanaa; Rabbuhum a\'lamu bihim; qaalal lazeena ghalaboo \'alaaa amrihim lanat takhizanna \'alaihim masjidaa\n\n  Thus did We make their case known to the people, that they might know that the promise of Allah is true, and that there can be no doubt about the Hour of Judgment. Behold, they dispute among themselves as to their affair. (Some) said Construct a building over them: their Lord knows best about them: those who prevailed over their affair said Let us surely build a place of worship over them. (21)\n\nسَيَقُولُونَ ثَلاثَةٌ رَّابِعُهُمْ كَلْبُهُمْ وَيَقُولُونَ خَمْسَةٌ سَادِسُهُمْ كَلْبُهُمْ رَجْمًا بِالْغَيْبِ وَيَقُولُونَ سَبْعَةٌ وَثَامِنُهُمْ كَلْبُهُمْ قُل رَّبِّي أَعْلَمُ بِعِدَّتِهِم مَّا يَعْلَمُهُمْ إِلاَّ قَلِيلٌ فَلا تُمَارِ فِيهِمْ إِلاَّ مِرَاء ظَاهِرًا وَلا تَسْتَفْتِ فِيهِم مِّنْهُمْ أَحَدًا\n\n\n Sa yaqooloona salaasatur raabi\'uhum kalbuhum wa yaqooloona khamsatun saadisuhum kalbuhum rajmam bilghaib; wa yaqooloona sab\'atunw wa saaminuhum kalbuhum; qur Rabbeee a\'lamu bi\'iddatihim maa ya\'lamuhum illaa qaleel; falaa tumaari feehim illaa miraaa\'an zaahiranw wa laa tastafti feehim minhum ahadaa\n\n  (Some) say they were three, the dog being the fourth among them; (others) say they were five, the dog being the sixth― doubtfully guessing at the unknown; (yet others) say they were seven, the dog being the eighth. Say thou: My Lord knoweth best their number; it is but few that know their (real case). Enter not, therefore, into controversies concerning them, except on a matter that is clear, nor consult any of them about (the affair of) the Sleepers. (22)\n\nوَلا تَقُولَنَّ لِشَيْءٍ إِنِّي فَاعِلٌ ذَلِكَ غَدًا\n\n\n Wa laa taqoolanna lishai\'in innee faa\'ilun zaalika ghadaa\n\n  Nor say of anything, I shall be sure to do so and so tomorrow― (23)\n\nإِلاَّ أَن يَشَاء اللَّهُ وَاذْكُر رَّبَّكَ إِذَا نَسِيتَ وَقُلْ عَسَى أَن يَهْدِيَنِ رَبِّي لِأَقْرَبَ مِنْ هَذَا رَشَدًا\n\n\n Illaaa any yashaaa\'al laah; wazkur Rabbaka izaa naseeta wa qul \'asaaa any yahdiyani Rabbee li aqraba min haazaa rashadaa\n\n  Without adding, So please Allah! And call thy Lord to mind when thou forgettest, and say I hope that my Lord will guide me ever closer (even) than this to the right road. (24)\n\nوَلَبِثُوا فِي كَهْفِهِمْ ثَلاثَ مِائَةٍ سِنِينَ وَازْدَادُوا تِسْعًا\n\n\n Wa labisoo fee kahfihim salaasa mi\'atin sineena wazdaadoo tis\'aa\n\n  So they stayed in their Cave three hundred years, and (some) add nine (more). (25)\n\nقُلِ اللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا لَبِثُوا لَهُ غَيْبُ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالأَرْضِ أَبْصِرْ بِهِ وَأَسْمِعْ مَا لَهُم مِّن دُونِهِ مِن وَلِيٍّ وَلا يُشْرِكُ فِي حُكْمِهِ أَحَدًا\n\n\n Qulil laahu a\'lamu bimaa labisoo lahoo ghaibus samaawaati wal ardi absir bihee wa asmi\'; maa lahum min doonihee minw waliyyinw wa laa yushriku fee hukmihee ahadaa\n\n  Say: Allah knows best how long they stayed: with Him is (the knowledge of) the secrets of the heavens and the earth: how clearly He sees, how finely He hears (everything)! They have no protector other than Him; nor does He share His Command with any person whatsoever. (26)\n\nوَاتْلُ مَا أُوحِيَ إِلَيْكَ مِن كِتَابِ رَبِّكَ لا مُبَدِّلَ لِكَلِمَاتِهِ وَلَن تَجِدَ مِن دُونِهِ مُلْتَحَدًا\n\n\n Watlu maaa oohiya ilaika min Kitaabi Rabbika laa mubaddila li Kalimaatihee wa lan tajida min doonihee multahadaa\n\n  And recite (and teach) what has been revealed to thee of the Book of thy Lord: none can change His Words, and none wilt thou find as a refuge other than Him. (27)\n\nوَاصْبِرْ نَفْسَكَ مَعَ الَّذِينَ يَدْعُونَ رَبَّهُم بِالْغَدَاةِ وَالْعَشِيِّ يُرِيدُونَ وَجْهَهُ وَلا تَعْدُ عَيْنَاكَ عَنْهُمْ تُرِيدُ زِينَةَ الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَلا تُطِعْ مَنْ أَغْفَلْنَا قَلْبَهُ عَن ذِكْرِنَا وَاتَّبَعَ هَوَاهُ وَكَانَ أَمْرُهُ فُرُطًا\n\n\n Wasbir nafsaka ma\'al lazeena yad\'oona Rabbahum bilghadaati wal\'ashiyyi yureedoona Wajhahoo wa laa ta\'du \'aynaaka \'anhum tureedu zeenatal hayaatid dunyaa wa laa tuti\' man aghfalnaa qalbahoo \'an zikrinaa wattaba\'a hawaahu wa kaana amruhoo furutaa\n\n  And keep thy soul content with those who call on their Lord morning and evening, seeking His Face; and let not thine eyes pass beyond them seeking the pomp and glitter of this Life; nor obey any whose heart We have permitted to neglect the remembrance of Us, one who follows his own desires, whose case has gone beyond all bounds. (28)\n\nوَقُلِ الْحَقُّ مِن رَّبِّكُمْ فَمَن شَاء فَلْيُؤْمِن وَمَن شَاء فَلْيَكْفُرْ إِنَّا أَعْتَدْنَا لِلظَّالِمِينَ نَارًا أَحَاطَ بِهِمْ سُرَادِقُهَا وَإِن يَسْتَغِيثُوا يُغَاثُوا بِمَاء كَالْمُهْلِ يَشْوِي الْوُجُوهَ بِئْسَ الشَّرَابُ وَسَاءَتْ مُرْتَفَقًا\n\n\n Wa qulil haqqu mir Rabbikum faman shaaa\'a falyu minw wa man shaaa\'a falyakfur; innaaa a\'tadnaa lizzaalimeena Naaran ahaata bihim suraadiquhaa; wa iny yastagheesoo yaghaasoo bimaaa\'in kalmuhli yashwil wujooh\' bi\'sash-sharaab; wa saaa\'at murtafaqaa\n\n  Say The Truth is from your Lord: let him who will, believe, and let him who will, reject (it): for the wrongdoers We have prepared a Fire whose (smoke and flames), like the walls and roof of a tent will hem them in: if they implore relief they will be granted water like melted brass, that will scald their faces. How dreadful the drink! How uncomfortable a couch to recline on! (29)\n\nإِنَّ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ إِنَّا لا نُضِيعُ أَجْرَ مَنْ أَحْسَنَ عَمَلا\n\n\n Innal lazeena aamanoo wa \'amilus saalihaati innaa laa nudee\'u ajra man ahsana \'amalaa\n\n  As to those who believe and work righteousness, verily We shall not suffer to perish the reward of any who do a (single) righteous deed. (30)\n\nأُوْلَئِكَ لَهُمْ جَنَّاتُ عَدْنٍ تَجْرِي مِن تَحْتِهِمُ الأَنْهَارُ يُحَلَّوْنَ فِيهَا مِنْ أَسَاوِرَ مِن ذَهَبٍ وَيَلْبَسُونَ ثِيَابًا خُضْرًا مِّن سُندُسٍ وَإِسْتَبْرَقٍ مُّتَّكِئِينَ فِيهَا عَلَى الأَرَائِكِ نِعْمَ الثَّوَابُ وَحَسُنَتْ مُرْتَفَقًا\n\n\n Ulaaa\'ika lahum Jannaatu \'Adnin tajree min tahtihimul anhaaru yuhallawna feehaa min asaawira min zahabinw wa yalbasoona siyaaban khudram min sundusinw wa istabraqim muttaki\'eena feehaa \'alal araaa\'ik; ni\'mas sawaab; wa hasunat murtafaqaa\n\n  For them will be Gardens of Eternity; beneath them rivers will flow; they will be adorned therein with bracelets of gold, and they will wear green garments of fine silk and heavy brocade; they will recline therein on raised thrones. How good the recompense! How beautiful a couch to recline on! (31)\n\nوَاضْرِبْ لَهُم مَّثَلا رَّجُلَيْنِ جَعَلْنَا لِأَحَدِهِمَا جَنَّتَيْنِ مِنْ أَعْنَابٍ وَحَفَفْنَاهُمَا بِنَخْلٍ وَجَعَلْنَا بَيْنَهُمَا زَرْعًا\n\n\n Wadrib lahum masalar rajulaini ja\'alnaa li ahadihimaa jannataini min a\'naabinw wa hafafnaahumaa binakhilinw wa ja\'alnaa bainahumaa zar\'aa\n\n  Set forth to them the parable of two men: for one of them We provided two gardens of grapevines and surrounded them with date-palms: in between the two We placed corn-fields. (32)\n\nكِلْتَا الْجَنَّتَيْنِ آتَتْ أُكُلَهَا وَلَمْ تَظْلِمْ مِنْهُ شَيْئًا وَفَجَّرْنَا خِلالَهُمَا نَهَرًا\n\n\n Kiltal jannataini aatat ukulahaa wa lam tazlim minhu shai\'anw wa fajjarnaa khi laalahumaa naharaa\n\n  Each of those gardens brought forth its produce, and failed not in the least therein: in the midst of them We caused a river to flow. (33)\n\nوَكَانَ لَهُ ثَمَرٌ فَقَالَ لِصَاحِبِهِ وَهُوَ يُحَاوِرُهُ أَنَا أَكْثَرُ مِنكَ مَالا وَأَعَزُّ نَفَرًا\n\n\n Wa kaana lahoo samarun faqaala lisaahibihee wa huwa yuhaawiruhoo ana aksaru minka maalanw wa a\'azzu nafaraa\n\n  (Abundant) was the produce this man had: he said to his companion, in the course of a mutual argument: More wealth have I than you, and more honour and power in (my following of) men. (34)\n\nوَدَخَلَ جَنَّتَهُ وَهُوَ ظَالِمٌ لِّنَفْسِهِ قَالَ مَا أَظُنُّ أَن تَبِيدَ هَذِهِ أَبَدًا\n\n\n Wa dakhala jannatahoo wa huwa zaalimul linafsihee qaala maaa azunnu an tabeeda haaziheee abadaa\n\n  He went into his garden in a state (of mind) unjust to his soul: He said I deem not that this will ever perish. (35)\n\nوَمَا أَظُنُّ السَّاعَةَ قَائِمَةً وَلَئِن رُّدِدتُّ إِلَى رَبِّي لَأَجِدَنَّ خَيْرًا مِّنْهَا مُنقَلَبًا\n\n\n Wa maaa azunnus Saa\'ata qaaa\'imatanw wa la\'ir rudittu ilaa Rabbee la ajidanna khairam minhaa munqalabaa\n\n  Nor do I deem that the Hour (of Judgment) will (ever) come: even if I am brought back to my Lord I shall surely find (there) something better in exchange. (36)\n\nقَالَ لَهُ صَاحِبُهُ وَهُوَ يُحَاوِرُهُ أَكَفَرْتَ بِالَّذِي خَلَقَكَ مِن تُرَابٍ ثُمَّ مِن نُّطْفَةٍ ثُمَّ سَوَّاكَ رَجُلا\n\n\n Qaala lahoo saahibuhoo wa huwa yuhaawiruhooo akafarta billazee khalaqaka min turaabin summa min nutfatin summa sawwaaka rajulaa\n\n  His companion said to him, in the course of the argument with him: Dost thou deny Him Who created thee out of dust then out of a sperm-drop, then fashioned thee into a man? (37)\n\nلَّكِنَّا هُوَ اللَّهُ رَبِّي وَلا أُشْرِكُ بِرَبِّي أَحَدًا\n\n\n Laakinaa Huwal laahu Rabbee wa laa ushriku bi Rabbeee ahadaa\n\n  But (I think) for my part that he is Allah, my Lord, and none shall I associate with my Lord. (38)\n\nوَلَوْلا إِذْ دَخَلْتَ جَنَّتَكَ قُلْتَ مَا شَاء اللَّهُ لا قُوَّةَ إِلاَّ بِاللَّهِ إِن تَرَنِ أَنَا أَقَلَّ مِنكَ مَالا وَوَلَدًا\n\n\n Wa law laaa iz dakhalta jannataka qulta maa shaaa\'al laahu laa quwwata illaa billaah; in tarani ana aqalla minka maalanw wa waladaa\n\n  Why didst thou not, as thou wentest into thy garden, say: `Allah\'s Will (be done)! There is no power but with Allah!\' If thou dost see me less than thee in wealth and sons (39)\n\nفَعَسَى رَبِّي أَن يُؤْتِيَنِ خَيْرًا مِّن جَنَّتِكَ وَيُرْسِلَ عَلَيْهَا حُسْبَانًا مِّنَ السَّمَاء فَتُصْبِحَ صَعِيدًا زَلَقًا\n\n\n Fa\'asaa Rabeee any yu\'tiyani khairam min jannatika wa yursila \'alaihaa husbaanam minas samaaa\'i fatusbiha sa\'eedan zalaqaa\n\n  It may be that my Lord will give me something better than thy garden, and that He will send on thy garden thunderbolts (by way of reckoning) from heaven, making it (but) slippery sand!― (40)\n\nأَوْ يُصْبِحَ مَاؤُهَا غَوْرًا فَلَن تَسْتَطِيعَ لَهُ طَلَبًا\n\n\n Aw yusbiha maaa\'uhaaa ghawran falan tastatee\'a lahoo talabaa\n\n  Or the water of the garden will run off underground so that thou wilt never be able to find it. (41)\n\nوَأُحِيطَ بِثَمَرِهِ فَأَصْبَحَ يُقَلِّبُ كَفَّيْهِ عَلَى مَا أَنفَقَ فِيهَا وَهِيَ خَاوِيَةٌ عَلَى عُرُوشِهَا وَيَقُولُ يَا لَيْتَنِي لَمْ أُشْرِكْ بِرَبِّي أَحَدًا\n\n\n Wa uheeta bisamarihee faasbaha yuqallibu kaffaihi \'alaa maaa anfaqa feehaa wa hiya khaawiyatun \'alaa \'urooshihaa wa yaqoolu yaalaitanee lam ushrik bi Rabbeee ahadaa\n\n  So his fruits (and enjoyment) were encompassed (with ruin), and he remained twisting and turning his hands over what he had spent on his property, which had (now) tumbled to pieces to its very foundations, and he could only say Woe is me! would I had never ascribed partners to my Lord and Cherisher! (42)\n\nوَلَمْ تَكُن لَّهُ فِئَةٌ يَنصُرُونَهُ مِن دُونِ اللَّهِ وَمَا كَانَ مُنتَصِرًا\n\n\n Wa lam takul lahoo fi\'atuny yansuroonahoo min doonil laahi wa maa kaana muntasiraa\n\n  Nor had he numbers to help him against Allah, nor was he able to deliver himself. (43)\n\nهُنَالِكَ الْوَلايَةُ لِلَّهِ الْحَقِّ هُوَ خَيْرٌ ثَوَابًا وَخَيْرٌ عُقْبًا\n\n\n Hunaalikal walaayatu lillaahil haqq; huwa khairun sawaabanw wa khairun \'uqbaa (section 5)\n\n  There, the (only) protection comes from Allah, the True One. He is the Best to reward and the Best to give success. (44)\n\nوَاضْرِبْ لَهُم مَّثَلَ الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا كَمَاء أَنزَلْنَاهُ مِنَ السَّمَاء فَاخْتَلَطَ بِهِ نَبَاتُ الأَرْضِ فَأَصْبَحَ هَشِيمًا تَذْرُوهُ الرِّيَاحُ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَلَى كُلِّ شَيْءٍ مُّقْتَدِرًا\n\n\n Wadrib lahum masalal hayaatid dunyaa kamaaa\'in anzalnaahu minas samaaa\'i fakhtalata bihee nabaatul ardi fa asbaha hasheeman tazroo hur riyaah; wa kaanal laahu \'alaa kulli shai\'im muqtadiraa\n\n  Set forth to them the similitude of the life of this world: it is like the rain which We send down from the skies: the earth\'s vegetation absorbs it, But soon it becomes dry stubble, which the winds do scatter: it is (only) Allah Who prevails over all things. (45)\n\nالْمَالُ وَالْبَنُونَ زِينَةُ الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَالْبَاقِيَاتُ الصَّالِحَاتُ خَيْرٌ عِندَ رَبِّكَ ثَوَابًا وَخَيْرٌ أَمَلا\n\n\n Almaalu walbanoona zeenatul hayaatid dunya wal baaqiyaatus saalihaatu khairun \'inda Rabbika sawaabanw wa khairun amalaa\n\n  Wealth and sons are allurements of the life of this world: but the things that endure, Good Deeds, are best in the sight of thy Lord, as rewards, and best as (the foundation for) hopes. (46)\n\nوَيَوْمَ نُسَيِّرُ الْجِبَالَ وَتَرَى الأَرْضَ بَارِزَةً وَحَشَرْنَاهُمْ فَلَمْ نُغَادِرْ مِنْهُمْ أَحَدًا\n\n\n Wa yawma nusaiyirul jibaala wa taral arda baariza tanw wa hasharnaahum falam nughaadir minhum ahadaa\n\n  One Day We shall remove the mountains, and thou wilt see the earth as a level stretch, and We shall gather them, all together, nor shall We leave out any one of them. (47)\n\nوَعُرِضُوا عَلَى رَبِّكَ صَفًّا لَّقَدْ جِئْتُمُونَا كَمَا خَلَقْنَاكُمْ أَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ بَلْ زَعَمْتُمْ أَلَّن نَّجْعَلَ لَكُم مَّوْعِدًا\n\n\n Wa \'uridoo \'alaa Rabbika saffaa, laqad ji\'tumoonaa kamaa khalaqnaakum awala marrah; bal za\'amtum allannaj\'ala lakum maw\'idaa\n\n  And they will be marshalled before thy Lord in ranks (with the announcement), Now have ye come to Us (bare) as We created you first: aye, ye thought We shall not fulfil the appointment made to you to meet (Us)!: (48)\n\nوَوُضِعَ الْكِتَابُ فَتَرَى الْمُجْرِمِينَ مُشْفِقِينَ مِمَّا فِيهِ وَيَقُولُونَ يَا وَيْلَتَنَا مَالِ هَذَا الْكِتَابِ لا يُغَادِرُ صَغِيرَةً وَلا كَبِيرَةً إِلاَّ أَحْصَاهَا وَوَجَدُوا مَا عَمِلُوا حَاضِرًا وَلا يَظْلِمُ رَبُّكَ أَحَدًا\n\n\n Wa wudi\'al kitaabu fataral mujrimeena mushfiqeena mimmaa feehi wa yaqooloona yaa wailatanaa maa lihaazal kitaabi laa yughaadiru saghee ratanw wa laa kabeeratan illaaa ahsaahaa; wa wajadoo maa \'amiloo haadiraa; wa laa yazlimu Rabbuka ahadaa\n\n  And the Book (of Deeds) will be placed (before you); and thou wilt see the sinful in great terror because of what is (recorded) therein; they will say Ah! woe to us! what a book is this! It leaves out nothing small or great, but takes account thereof! They will find all that they did, placed before them: and not one will thy Lord treat with injustice. (49)\n\nوَإِذْ قُلْنَا لِلْمَلائِكَةِ اسْجُدُوا لآدَمَ فَسَجَدُوا إِلاَّ إِبْلِيسَ كَانَ مِنَ الْجِنِّ فَفَسَقَ عَنْ أَمْرِ رَبِّهِ أَفَتَتَّخِذُونَهُ وَذُرِّيَّتَهُ أَوْلِيَاء مِن دُونِي وَهُمْ لَكُمْ عَدُوٌّ بِئْسَ لِلظَّالِمِينَ بَدَلا\n\n\n Wa iz qulnaa lilma laaa\'ikatis judoo li Aadama fasajadooo illaaa Ibleesa kaana minal jinni fafasaqa \'an amri Rabbih; afatattakhizoonahoo wa zurriyatahooo awliyaaa\'a min doonee wa hum lakum \'aduww; bi\'sa lizzaalimeena badalaa\n\n  Behold! We said to the angels Bow down to Adam: they bowed down except Iblis. He was one of the Jinns, and he broke the Command of his Lord. Will ye then take him and his progeny as protectors rather than Me? And they are enemies to you! Evil would be the exchange for the wrongdoers! (50)\n\nمَا أَشْهَدتُّهُمْ خَلْقَ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالأَرْضِ وَلا خَلْقَ أَنفُسِهِمْ وَمَا كُنتُ مُتَّخِذَ الْمُضِلِّينَ عَضُدًا\n\n\n Maaa ash hattuhum khalqas samaawaati wal ardi wa laa khalqa anfusihim wa maa kuntu muttakizal mudilleena \'adudaa\n\n  I called them not to witness the creation of the heavens and the earth, nor (even) their own creation: nor is it for Me to take as helpers such as lead (men) astray! (51)\n\nوَيَوْمَ يَقُولُ نَادُوا شُرَكَائِيَ الَّذِينَ زَعَمْتُمْ فَدَعَوْهُمْ فَلَمْ يَسْتَجِيبُوا لَهُمْ وَجَعَلْنَا بَيْنَهُم مَّوْبِقًا\n\n\n Wa Yawma yaqoolu naadoo shurakaaa\'i yal lazeena za\'amtum fada\'awhum falam yastajeeboo lahum wa ja\'alnaa bainahum maw biqaa\n\n  One Day He will say Call on those whom ye thought to be My partners and they will call on them but they will not listen to them; and We shall make for them a place of common perdition. (52)\n\nوَرَأَى الْمُجْرِمُونَ النَّارَ فَظَنُّوا أَنَّهُم مُّوَاقِعُوهَا وَلَمْ يَجِدُوا عَنْهَا مَصْرِفًا\n\n\n Wa ra al mujrimoonan Naara fazannooo annahum muwaaqi\'oohaa wa lam yajidoo \'anhaa masrifaa\n\n  And the Sinful shall see the Fire and apprehend that they have to fall therein; no means will they find to turn away therefrom. (53)\n\nوَلَقَدْ صَرَّفْنَا فِي هَذَا الْقُرْآنِ لِلنَّاسِ مِن كُلِّ مَثَلٍ وَكَانَ الإِنسَانُ أَكْثَرَ شَيْءٍ جَدَلا\n\n\n Wa laqad sarrafnaa fee haazal quraani linnaasi mn kulli masal; wa kaanal insaanu aksara shai\'in jadalaa\n\n  We have explained in detail in this Qur\'an, for the benefit of mankind, every kind of similitude: but man is, in most things contentious. (54)\n\nوَمَا مَنَعَ النَّاسَ أَن يُؤْمِنُوا إِذْ جَاءَهُمُ الْهُدَى وَيَسْتَغْفِرُوا رَبَّهُمْ إِلاَّ أَن تَأْتِيَهُمْ سُنَّةُ الأَوَّلِينَ أَوْ يَأْتِيَهُمُ الْعَذَابُ قُبُلا\n\n\n Wa maa mana\'an naasa any yu\'minooo iz jaaa\'ahumul hudaa wa yastaghfiroo Rabbahum illaaa an taatiyahum sunnatul awwaleena aw yaatiyahumul \'azaabu qubulaa\n\n  And what is there to keep back men from believing, now that guidance has come to them nor from praying for forgiveness from their Lord, but that (they ask that) the ways of the ancients be repeated with them, or the Wrath be brought to them face to face? (55)\n\nوَمَا نُرْسِلُ الْمُرْسَلِينَ إِلاَّ مُبَشِّرِينَ وَمُنذِرِينَ وَيُجَادِلُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا بِالْبَاطِلِ لِيُدْحِضُوا بِهِ الْحَقَّ وَاتَّخَذُوا آيَاتِي وَمَا أُنذِرُوا هُزُوًا\n\n\n Wa maa nursilul mursaleena illaa mubashshireena wa munzireen; wa yujaadilul lazeena kafaroo bilbaatili liyudhidoo bihil haqqa wattakhazooo Aayaatee wa maaa unziroo huzuwaa\n\n  We only send the Messengers to give glad tidings and to give warnings: but the Unbelievers dispute with vain argument, in order therewith to weaken the truth, and they treat My Signs as a jest, as also the fact that they are warned! (56)\n\nوَمَنْ أَظْلَمُ مِمَّن ذُكِّرَ بِآيَاتِ رَبِّهِ فَأَعْرَضَ عَنْهَا وَنَسِيَ مَا قَدَّمَتْ يَدَاهُ إِنَّا جَعَلْنَا عَلَى قُلُوبِهِمْ أَكِنَّةً أَن يَفْقَهُوهُ وَفِي آذَانِهِمْ وَقْرًا وَإِن تَدْعُهُمْ إِلَى الْهُدَى فَلَن يَهْتَدُوا إِذًا أَبَدًا\n\n\n Wa man azlamu mimman zukkira bi ayaati Rabbihee fa-a\'rada \'anhaa wa nasiya maa qaddamat yadaah; innaa ja\'alnaa \'alaa quloobihim akinnatan any yafqahoohu wa feee aazaanihim waqraa; wa in tad\'uhum ilal hudaa falany yahtadooo izan abadaa\n\n  And who doth more wrong than one who is reminded of the Signs of his Lord but turns away from them, forgetting the (deeds) which his hands have sent forth? Verily We have set veils over their hearts lest they should understand this, and over their ears, deafness. If thou callest them to guidance, even then will they never accept guidance. (57)\n\nوَرَبُّكَ الْغَفُورُ ذُو الرَّحْمَةِ لَوْ يُؤَاخِذُهُم بِمَا كَسَبُوا لَعَجَّلَ لَهُمُ الْعَذَابَ بَل لَّهُم مَّوْعِدٌ لَّن يَجِدُوا مِن دُونِهِ مَوْئِلا\n\n\n Wa Rabbukal Ghafooru zur rahmati law yu\'aakhi zuhum bimaa kasaboo la\'ajala lahumul \'azaab; bal lahum maw\'idul lany yajidoo min doonihee maw\'ilaa\n\n  But your Lord is Most Forgiving, Full of Mercy. If He were to call them (at once) to account for what they have earned, then surely He would have hastened their Punishment: but they have their appointed time, beyond which they will find no refuge. (58)\n\nوَتِلْكَ الْقُرَى أَهْلَكْنَاهُمْ لَمَّا ظَلَمُوا وَجَعَلْنَا لِمَهْلِكِهِم مَّوْعِدًا\n\n\n Wa tkal quraaa ahlak nahum lammaa zulamoo wa ja\'alnaa limahlikihim maw\'idaa\n\n  Such were the populations We destroyed when they committed iniquities; but We fixed an appointed time for their destruction. (59)\n\nوَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَى لِفَتَاهُ لا أَبْرَحُ حَتَّى أَبْلُغَ مَجْمَعَ الْبَحْرَيْنِ أَوْ أَمْضِيَ حُقُبًا\n\n\n Wa iz qaalaa Moosaa lifataahu laaa abrahu hattaaa ablugha majma\'al bahrayni aw amdiya huqubaa\n\n  Behold, Moses said to his attendant I will not give up until I reach the junction of the two seas or (until) I spend years and years in travel. (60)\n\nفَلَمَّا بَلَغَا مَجْمَعَ بَيْنِهِمَا نَسِيَا حُوتَهُمَا فَاتَّخَذَ سَبِيلَهُ فِي الْبَحْرِ سَرَبًا\n\n\n Falammaa balaghaa majma\'a bainihimaa nasiyaa hootahumaa fattakhaza sabeelahoo fil bahri sarabaa\n\n  But when they reached the Junction, they forgot (about) their Fish, which took its course through the sea (straight) as in a tunnel. (61)\n\nفَلَمَّا جَاوَزَا قَالَ لِفَتَاهُ آتِنَا غَدَاءَنَا لَقَدْ لَقِينَا مِن سَفَرِنَا هَذَا نَصَبًا\n\n\n Falammaa jaawazaa qaala lifataahu aatinaa ghadaaa\'anaa laqad laqeena min safarinaa haazaa nasabaa\n\n  When they had passed on (some distance), Moses said to his attendant: Bring us our early meal; truly we have suffered much fatigue at this (stage of) our journey. (62)\n\nقَالَ أَرَأَيْتَ إِذْ أَوَيْنَا إِلَى الصَّخْرَةِ فَإِنِّي نَسِيتُ الْحُوتَ وَمَا أَنسَانِيهُ إِلاَّ الشَّيْطَانُ أَنْ أَذْكُرَهُ وَاتَّخَذَ سَبِيلَهُ فِي الْبَحْرِ عَجَبًا\n\n\n Qaala ara\'ayta iz awainaaa ilas sakhrati fa innee naseetul hoota wa maaa ansaaneehu illash Shaitaanu an azkurah; wattakhaza sabeelahoo fil bahri\'ajabaa\n\n  He replied: Sawest thou (what happened) when we betook ourselves to the rock? I did indeed forget (about) the Fish: none but Satan made me forget to tell (you) about it: it took its course through the sea in a marvelous way! (63)\n\nقَالَ ذَلِكَ مَا كُنَّا نَبْغِ فَارْتَدَّا عَلَى آثَارِهِمَا قَصَصًا\n\n\n Qaala zaalika maa kunnaa nabgh; fartaddaa \'alaa aasaari him maa qasasaa\n\n  Moses said: That was what we were seeking after: so they went back on their footsteps, following (the path they had come). (64)\n\nفَوَجَدَا عَبْدًا مِّنْ عِبَادِنَا آتَيْنَاهُ رَحْمَةً مِنْ عِندِنَا وَعَلَّمْنَاهُ مِن لَّدُنَّا عِلْمًا\n\n\n Fa wajadaa \'abdam min \'ibaadinaaa aatainaahu Rahmatam min \'indinaa wa \'allamnaahu mil ladunnaa \'ilmaa\n\n  So they found one of Our servants on whom We had bestowed Mercy from Ourselves and whom We had taught knowledge from Our own presence. (65)\n\nقَالَ لَهُ مُوسَى هَلْ أَتَّبِعُكَ عَلَى أَن تُعَلِّمَنِ مِمَّا عُلِّمْتَ رُشْدًا\n\n\n Qaala lahoo Moosaa hal attabi\'uka \'alaaa an tu\'allimani mimmaa \'ullimta rushdaa\n\n  Moses said to him: May I follow thee, on the footing that thou teach me something of the (Higher) Truth which thou hast been taught? (66)\n\nقَالَ إِنَّكَ لَن تَسْتَطِيعَ مَعِيَ صَبْرًا\n\n\n Qaalaa innaka lan tastatee\'a ma\'iya sabraa\n\n  (The other) said: Verily thou wilt not be able to have patience with me! (67)\n\nوَكَيْفَ تَصْبِرُ عَلَى مَا لَمْ تُحِطْ بِهِ خُبْرًا\n\n\n Wa kaifa tasbiru \'alaa maa lam tuhit bihee khubraa\n\n  And how canst thou have patience about things about which thy understanding is not complete? (68)\n\nقَالَ سَتَجِدُنِي إِن شَاء اللَّهُ صَابِرًا وَلا أَعْصِي لَكَ أَمْرًا\n\n\n Qaala satajiduneee in shaa \'al laahu saabiranw wa laaa a\'see laka amraa\n\n  Moses said: Thou wilt find me, if Allah so will (truly) patient: nor shall I disobey thee in aught. (69)\n\nقَالَ فَإِنِ اتَّبَعْتَنِي فَلا تَسْأَلْنِي عَن شَيْءٍ حَتَّى أُحْدِثَ لَكَ مِنْهُ ذِكْرًا\n\n\n Qaala fa init taba\'tanee falaa tas\'alnee \'an shai\'in hattaaa uhdisa laka minhu zikraa (section 9)\n\n  The other said: If then thou wouldst follow me, ask me no questions about anything until I myself speak to thee concerning it. (70)\n\nفَانطَلَقَا حَتَّى إِذَا رَكِبَا فِي السَّفِينَةِ خَرَقَهَا قَالَ أَخَرَقْتَهَا لِتُغْرِقَ أَهْلَهَا لَقَدْ جِئْتَ شَيْئًا إِمْرًا\n\n\n Fantalaqaa hattaaa izaa rakibaa fis safeenati kharaqahaa qaala akharaqtahaa litughriqa ahlahaa laqad ji\'ta shai\'an imraa\n\n  So they both proceeded: until, when they were in the boat, he scuttled it. Said Moses: Hast thou scuttled it in order to drown those in it? Truly a strange thing hast thou done! (71)\n\nقَالَ أَلَمْ أَقُلْ إِنَّكَ لَن تَسْتَطِيعَ مَعِيَ صَبْرًا\n\n\n Qaala alam aqul innaka lan tastatee\'a ma\'iya sabraa\n\n  He answered: Did I not tell thee that thou canst have no patience with me? (72)\n\nقَالَ لا تُؤَاخِذْنِي بِمَا نَسِيتُ وَلا تُرْهِقْنِي مِنْ أَمْرِي عُسْرًا\n\n\n Qaala laa tu\'aakhiznee bimaa naseetu wa laa turhiqnee min amree \'usraa\n\n  Moses said: Rebuke me not for forgetting, nor grieve me by raising difficulties in my case. (73)\n\nفَانطَلَقَا حَتَّى إِذَا لَقِيَا غُلامًا فَقَتَلَهُ قَالَ أَقَتَلْتَ نَفْسًا زَكِيَّةً بِغَيْرِ نَفْسٍ لَّقَدْ جِئْتَ شَيْئًا نُّكْرًا\n\n\n Fantalaqaa hattaa izaa laqiyaa ghulaaman faqatalahoo qaala aqatalta nafsan zakiy yatam bighairi nafs; laqad ji\'ta shai\'an nukraa (End Juz 15)\n\n  Then they proceeded: until, when they met a young man, he slew him. Moses said: Hast thou slain an innocent person who had slain none? Truly a foul (unheard-of) thing hast thou done! (74)\n\nقَالَ أَلَمْ أَقُل لَّكَ إِنَّكَ لَن تَسْتَطِيعَ مَعِي صَبْرًا\n\n\n Qaala alam aqul laka innaka lan tastatee\'a ma\'iya sabraa\n\n  He answered: Did I not tell thee that thou canst have no patience with me? (75)\n\nقَالَ إِن سَأَلْتُكَ عَن شَيْءٍ بَعْدَهَا فَلا تُصَاحِبْنِي قَدْ بَلَغْتَ مِن لَّدُنِّي عُذْرًا\n\n\n Qaala in sa altuka \'an shai\'im ba\'dahaa falaa tusaahibnee qad balaghta mil ladunnee \'uzraa\n\n  (Moses) said: If ever I ask thee about anything after this, keep me not in thy company: then wouldst thou have received (full) excuse from my side. (76)\n\nفَانطَلَقَا حَتَّى إِذَا أَتَيَا أَهْلَ قَرْيَةٍ اسْتَطْعَمَا أَهْلَهَا فَأَبَوْا أَن يُضَيِّفُوهُمَا فَوَجَدَا فِيهَا جِدَارًا يُرِيدُ أَنْ يَنقَضَّ فَأَقَامَهُ قَالَ لَوْ شِئْتَ لاتَّخَذْتَ عَلَيْهِ أَجْرًا\n\n\n Fantalaqaa hattaaa izaaa atayaaa ahla qaryatinis tat\'amaaa ahlahaa fa abaw any yudaiyifoohumaa fawajadaa feehaa jidaarany yureedu any yanqadda fa aqaamah; qaala law shi\'ta lattakhazta \'alaihi ajraa\n\n  Then they proceeded: until, when they came to the inhabitants of a town, they asked them for food, but they refused them hospitality. They found there a wall on the point of falling down, but he set it up straight. (Moses) said: If thou hadst wished, surely thou couldst have exacted some recompense for it! (77)\n\nقَالَ هَذَا فِرَاقُ بَيْنِي وَبَيْنِكَ سَأُنَبِّئُكَ بِتَأْوِيلِ مَا لَمْ تَسْتَطِع عَّلَيْهِ صَبْرًا\n\n\n Qaala haazaa firaaqu bainee wa bainik; sa unabi \'uka bitaaweeli maa lam tastati\' \'alaihi sabraa\n\n  He answered: This is the parting between me and thee: now will I tell thee the interpretation of (those things) over which thou wast unable to hold patience. (78)\n\nأَمَّا السَّفِينَةُ فَكَانَتْ لِمَسَاكِينَ يَعْمَلُونَ فِي الْبَحْرِ فَأَرَدتُّ أَنْ أَعِيبَهَا وَكَانَ وَرَاءهُم مَّلِكٌ يَأْخُذُ كُلَّ سَفِينَةٍ غَصْبًا\n\n\n Ammas safeenatu fakaanat limasaakeena ya\'maloona fil bahri fa arattu an a\'eebahaa wa kaana waraaa\' ahum malikuny yaakhuzu kulla safeenatin ghasbaa\n\n  As for the boat, it belonged to certain men in dire want: they plied on the water: I but wished to render it unserviceable, for there was after them a certain king who seized on every boat by force. (79)\n\nوَأَمَّا الْغُلامُ فَكَانَ أَبَوَاهُ مُؤْمِنَيْنِ فَخَشِينَا أَن يُرْهِقَهُمَا طُغْيَانًا وَكُفْرًا\n\n\n Wa aammal ghulaamu fakaana abawaahu mu\'minaini fakhasheenaaa any yurhiqa humaa tughyaananw wa kufraa\n\n  As for the youth his parents were people of Faith, and we feared that he would grieve them by obstinate rebellion and ingratitude (to Allah and man). (80)\n\nفَأَرَدْنَا أَن يُبْدِلَهُمَا رَبُّهُمَا خَيْرًا مِّنْهُ زَكَاةً وَأَقْرَبَ رُحْمًا\n\n\n Faradnaa any yubdila humaa Rabbuhumaa khairam minhu zakaatanw wa aqraba ruhmaa\n\n  So we desired that their Lord would give them in exchange (a son) better in purity (of conduct) and closer in affection. (81)\n\nوَأَمَّا الْجِدَارُ فَكَانَ لِغُلامَيْنِ يَتِيمَيْنِ فِي الْمَدِينَةِ وَكَانَ تَحْتَهُ كَنزٌ لَّهُمَا وَكَانَ أَبُوهُمَا صَالِحًا فَأَرَادَ رَبُّكَ أَنْ يَبْلُغَا أَشُدَّهُمَا وَيَسْتَخْرِجَا كَنزَهُمَا رَحْمَةً مِّن رَّبِّكَ وَمَا فَعَلْتُهُ عَنْ أَمْرِي ذَلِكَ تَأْوِيلُ مَا لَمْ تَسْطِع عَّلَيْهِ صَبْرًا\n\n\n Wa ammal jidaaru fakaana lighulaamaini yateemaini fil madeenati wa kaana tahtahoo kanzul lahumaa wa kaana aboohumaa saalihan fa araada Rabbuka any yablughaaa ashuddahumaa wa yastakhrijaa kanzahumaa rahmatam mir Rabbik; wa maa fa\'altuhoo \'an amree; zaalika taaweelu maa lam tasti\' \'alaihi sabra\n\n  As for the wall it, belonged to two youths, orphans in the Town; there was, beneath it, a buried treasure, to which they were entitled: their father had been a righteous man: so thy Lord desired that they should attain their age of full strength and get out their treasure― a mercy (and favour) from thy Lord. I did it not of my own accord. Such is the interpretation of (those things) over which thou wast unable to hold patience. (82)\n\nوَيَسْأَلُونَكَ عَن ذِي الْقَرْنَيْنِ قُلْ سَأَتْلُو عَلَيْكُم مِّنْهُ ذِكْرًا\n\n\n Wa yas\'aloonaka \'an Zil Qarnaini qul sa atloo \'alaikum minhu zikraa\n\n  They ask thee concerning Dhu al Qarnayn. Say I will rehearse to you something of his story. (83)\n\nإِنَّا مَكَّنَّا لَهُ فِي الأَرْضِ وَآتَيْنَاهُ مِن كُلِّ شَيْءٍ سَبَبًا\n\n\n Innaa makkannaa lahoo fil ardi wa aatainaahu min kulli shai\'in sababaa\n\n  Verily We established his power on earth, and We gave him the ways and the means to all ends. (84)\n\nفَأَتْبَعَ سَبَبًا\n\n\n Fa atba\'a sababaa\n\n  One (such) way he followed, (85)\n\nحَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ مَغْرِبَ الشَّمْسِ وَجَدَهَا تَغْرُبُ فِي عَيْنٍ حَمِئَةٍ وَوَجَدَ عِندَهَا قَوْمًا قُلْنَا يَا ذَا الْقَرْنَيْنِ إِمَّا أَن تُعَذِّبَ وَإِمَّا أَن تَتَّخِذَ فِيهِمْ حُسْنًا\n\n\n Hattaaa izaa balagha maghribash shamsi wajadahaaa taghrubu fee \'aynin hami\'a tinw wa wajada \'indahaa qawmaa; qulnaa yaa Zal Qarnaini immaaa an tu\'az ziba wa immaaa an tattakhiza feehim husnaa\n\n  Until, when he reached the setting of the sun, he found it set in a spring of murky water: near it he found a People: We said: O Dhu al Qarnayn! (thou hast authority) either to punish them, or to treat them with, kindness. (86)\n\nقَالَ أَمَّا مَن ظَلَمَ فَسَوْفَ نُعَذِّبُهُ ثُمَّ يُرَدُّ إِلَى رَبِّهِ فَيُعَذِّبُهُ عَذَابًا نُّكْرًا\n\n\n Qaala amaa man zalama fasawfa nu\'azzibuhoo summa yuraddu ilaa Rabbihee fa yu \'azzibuhoo azaaban nukraa\n\n  He said: Whoever doth wrong, him shall we punish; then shall he be sent back to his Lord; and He will punish hreminder_typeim with a punishment unheard-of (before). (87)\n\nوَأَمَّا مَنْ آمَنَ وَعَمِلَ صَالِحًا فَلَهُ جَزَاء الْحُسْنَى وَسَنَقُولُ لَهُ مِنْ أَمْرِنَا يُسْرًا\n\n\n Wa ammaa man aamana wa \'amila saalihan falahoo jazaaa\'anil husnaa wa sanaqoolu lahoo min amrinaa yusraa\n\n  But whoever believes, and works righteousness he shall have a goodly reward, and easy will be his task as we order it by our command. (88)\n\nثُمَّ أَتْبَعَ سَبَبًا\n\n\n Summa atba\'a sababaa\n\n  Then followed he (another) way. (89)\n\nحَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ مَطْلِعَ الشَّمْسِ وَجَدَهَا تَطْلُعُ عَلَى قَوْمٍ لَّمْ نَجْعَل لَّهُم مِّن دُونِهَا سِتْرًا\n\n\n Hattaaa izaa balagha matli\'ash shamsi wajdahaa tatlu\'u alaa qawmil lam naj\'al lahum min doonihaa sitraa\n\n  Until, when he came to the rising of the sun, he found it rising on a people for whom We had provided no covering protection against the sun. (90)\n\nكَذَلِكَ وَقَدْ أَحَطْنَا بِمَا لَدَيْهِ خُبْرًا\n\n\n Kazaalika wa qad ahatnaa bimaa ladaihi khubraa\n\n  (He left them) as they were: We completely understood what was before him. (91)\n\nثُمَّ أَتْبَعَ سَبَبًا\n\n\n Summa atba\'a sababaa\n\n  Then followed he (another) way (92)\n\nحَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ بَيْنَ السَّدَّيْنِ وَجَدَ مِن دُونِهِمَا قَوْمًا لّا يَكَادُونَ يَفْقَهُونَ قَوْلا\n\n\n Hattaaa izaa balagha bainas saddaini wajada min doonihimaa qawmal laa yakaa doona yafqahoona qawlaa\n\n  Until, when he reached (a tract) between two mountains, he found, beneath them a people who scarcely understood a word. (93)\n\nقَالُوا يَا ذَا الْقَرْنَيْنِ إِنَّ يَأْجُوجَ وَمَأْجُوجَ مُفْسِدُونَ فِي الأَرْضِ فَهَلْ نَجْعَلُ لَكَ خَرْجًا عَلَى أَن تَجْعَلَ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَهُمْ سَدًّا\n\n\n Qaaloo yaa Zal qarnaini inna Yaajooja wa Maajooja mufsidoona fil ardi fahal naj\'alu laka kharjan \'alaaa an taj\'ala bainanaa wa bainahum saddas\n\n  They said: O Dhu al Qarnayn! the Gog and Magog (people) do great mischief on earth: shall we then render thee tribute in order that thou mightest erect a barrier between us and them? (94)\n\nقَالَ مَا مَكَّنِّي فِيهِ رَبِّي خَيْرٌ فَأَعِينُونِي بِقُوَّةٍ أَجْعَلْ بَيْنَكُمْ وَبَيْنَهُمْ رَدْمًا\n\n\n Qaala maa makkannee feehi Rabbee khairun fa-a\'eenoonee biquwwatin aj\'al bainakum wa bainahum radmaa\n\n  He said: (The power) in which my Lord has established me is better (than tribute): help me therefore with strength (and labour): I will erect a strong barrier between you and them: (95)\n\nآتُونِي زُبَرَ الْحَدِيدِ حَتَّى إِذَا سَاوَى بَيْنَ الصَّدَفَيْنِ قَالَ انفُخُوا حَتَّى إِذَا جَعَلَهُ نَارًا قَالَ آتُونِي أُفْرِغْ عَلَيْهِ قِطْرًا\n\n\n Aatoonee zubaral hadeed, hattaaa izaa saawaa bainas sadafaini qaalan fukhoo hattaaa izaa ja\'alahoo naaran qaala aatooneee ufrigh \'alaihi qitraa\n\n  Bring me blocks of iron. At length when he had filled up the space between the two steep mountain― sides, he said Blow (with your bellows). Then when he had made it (red) as fire he said: Bring me, that I may pour over it molten lead. (96)\n\nفَمَا اسْطَاعُوا أَن يَظْهَرُوهُ وَمَا اسْتَطَاعُوا لَهُ نَقْبًا\n\n\n Famas taa\'ooo any yazharoohu wa mastataa\'oo lahoo naqbaa\n\n  Thus were they made powerless to scale it or to dig through it. (97)\n\nقَالَ هَذَا رَحْمَةٌ مِّن رَّبِّي فَإِذَا جَاءَ وَعْدُ رَبِّي جَعَلَهُ دَكَّاء وَكَانَ وَعْدُ رَبِّي حَقًّا\n\n\n Qaala haaza rahmatummir Rabbee fa izaa jaaa\'a wa\'du Rabbee ja\'alahoo dakkaaa\'a; wa kaana; wa du Rabbee haqqaa\n\n  He said: This is a mercy from my Lord: but when the promise of my Lord comes to pass, He will make it into dust; and the promise of My Lord is true. (98)\n\nوَتَرَكْنَا بَعْضَهُمْ يَوْمَئِذٍ يَمُوجُ فِي بَعْضٍ وَنُفِخَ فِي الصُّورِ فَجَمَعْنَاهُمْ جَمْعًا\n\n\n Wa taraknaa ba\'dahum Yawma\'iziny yamooju fee ba\'dinw wa nufikha fis Soori fajama\'naahum jam\'aa\n\n  On that day We shall leave them to surge like waves on one another; the trumpet will be blown, and We shall collect them all together. (99)\n\nوَعَرَضْنَا جَهَنَّمَ يَوْمَئِذٍ لِّلْكَافِرِينَ عَرْضًا\n\n\n Wa \'aradnaa jahannama Yawma\'izil lilkaafireena \'ardaa\n\n  And We shall present Hell that day for Unbelievers to see, all spread out― (100)\n\nالَّذِينَ كَانَتْ أَعْيُنُهُمْ فِي غِطَاءٍ عَن ذِكْرِي وَكَانُوا لا يَسْتَطِيعُونَ سَمْعًا\n\n\n Allazeena kaanat a\'yunuhum fee ghitaaa\'in \'an zikree wa kaanoo la yastatee\'oona sam\'aa (section 11)\n\n  (Unbelievers) whose eyes had been under a veil from Remembrance of Me, and who had been unable even to hear. (101)\n\nأَفَحَسِبَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا أَن يَتَّخِذُوا عِبَادِي مِن دُونِي أَوْلِيَاء إِنَّا أَعْتَدْنَا جَهَنَّمَ لِلْكَافِرِينَ نُزُلا\n\n\n Afahasibal lazeena kafarooo any yattakhizoo \'ibaadee min dooneee awliyaaa\'; innaaa a\'tadnaa jahannama lilkaafi reena nuzulaa\n\n  Do the Unbelievers think that they can take my servants as protectors besides Me? Verily We have prepared Hell for the Unbelievers for (their) entertainment. (102)\n\nقُلْ هَلْ نُنَبِّئُكُمْ بِالأَخْسَرِينَ أَعْمَالا\n\n\n Qul hal nunabbi\'ukum bilakhsareena a\'maalaa\n\n  Say: Shall we tell you of those who lose most in respect of their deeds?― (103)\n\nالَّذِينَ ضَلَّ سَعْيُهُمْ فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَهُمْ يَحْسَبُونَ أَنَّهُمْ يُحْسِنُونَ صُنْعًا\n\n\n Allazeena dalla sa\'yuhum fil hayaatid dunyaa wa hum yahsaboona annahum yuhsinoona sun\'aa\n\n  Those whose efforts have been wasted in this life while they thought that they were acquiring good by their works? (104)\n\nأُوْلَئِكَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا بِآيَاتِ رَبِّهِمْ وَلِقَائِهِ فَحَبِطَتْ أَعْمَالُهُمْ فَلا نُقِيمُ لَهُمْ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ وَزْنًا\n\n\n Ulaaa\'ikal lazeena kafaroo bi aayaati Rabbihim wa liqaaa\'ihee fahabitat a\'maaluhum falaa nuqeemu lahum Yawmal Qiyaamati waznaa\n\n  They are those who deny the Signs of their Lord and the fact of their having to meet Him (in the Hereafter): vain will be their works, nor shall We on the Day of Judgment, give them any Weight. (105)\n\nذَلِكَ جَزَاؤُهُمْ جَهَنَّمُ بِمَا كَفَرُوا وَاتَّخَذُوا آيَاتِي وَرُسُلِي هُزُوًا\n\n\n Zaalika jazaaa\'uhum jahannamu bimaa kafaroo wattakhazooo Aayaatee wa Rusulee huzuwaa\n\n  That is their reward, Hell; because they rejected Faith, and took My Signs and My Messengers by way of jest. (106)\n\nإِنَّ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ كَانَتْ لَهُمْ جَنَّاتُ الْفِرْدَوْسِ نُزُلا\n\n\n Innal lazeena aamanoo wa \'amilus saalihaati kaanat lahum Jannaatul Firdawsi nuzulaa\n\n  As to those who believe and work righteous deeds, they have, for their entertainment, the Gardens of Paradise (107)\n\nخَالِدِينَ فِيهَا لا يَبْغُونَ عَنْهَا حِوَلا\n\n\n Khaalideena feeha la yabghoona \'anhaa hiwalaa\n\n  Wherein they shall dwell (for aye): no change will they wish for themselves. (108)\n\nقُل لَّوْ كَانَ الْبَحْرُ مِدَادًا لِّكَلِمَاتِ رَبِّي لَنَفِدَ الْبَحْرُ قَبْلَ أَن تَنفَدَ كَلِمَاتُ رَبِّي وَلَوْ جِئْنَا بِمِثْلِهِ مَدَدًا\n\n\n Qul law kaanal bahru midaadal lik Kalimaati Rabbee lanafidal bahru qabla an tanfada Kalimaatu Rabbee wa law ji\'naa bimislihee madadaa\n\n  Say: If the ocean were ink (wherewith to write out) the words of my Lord, sooner would the ocean be exhausted than would the words of my Lord, even if we added another ocean like it, for its aid. (109)\n\nقُلْ إِنَّمَا أَنَا بَشَرٌ مِّثْلُكُمْ يُوحَى إِلَيَّ أَنَّمَا إِلَهُكُمْ إِلَهٌ وَاحِدٌ فَمَن كَانَ يَرْجُو لِقَاء رَبِّهِ فَلْيَعْمَلْ عَمَلا صَالِحًا وَلا يُشْرِكْ بِعِبَادَةِ رَبِّهِ أَحَدًا\n\n Qul innamaaa ana basharum mislukum yoohaaa ilaiya annamaa ilaahukum Ilaahunw Waahid; faman kaana yarjoo liqaaa\'a Rabbihee falya\'mal \'amalan saalihanw wa laa yushrik bi\'ibaadati Rabbiheee ahadaa \n\nSay: I am but a man like yourselves, (but) the inspiration has come to me, that your God is one God: whoever expects to meet his Lord, let him work righteousness, and in the worship of his Lord, admit no one as partner. (110)</string>


    <string name="surat_almulk_text">\n\nبَارَكَ الَّذِي بِيَدِهِ الْمُلْكُ وَهُوَ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ \n\nTabaraka allathee biyadihi almulku wahuwa AAala kulli shayin qadeerun\n\nBlessed be He in Whose hands is the Kingdom of the universe and has power over all things.(1)\n\nالَّذِي خَلَقَ الْمَوْتَ وَالْحَيَاةَ لِيَبْلُوَكُمْ أَيُّكُمْ أَحْسَنُ عَمَلًا ۚ وَهُوَ الْعَزِيزُ الْغَفُورُ \n\nAllathee khalaqa almawta waalhayata liyabluwakum ayyukum ahsanu AAamalan wahuwa alAAazeezu alghafooru\n\nThe One Who created death and life, so that He may put you to test, to find out which of you is best in deeds: He is the All-Mighty, the All-Forgiving.(2)\n\nالَّذِي خَلَقَ سَبْعَ سَمَاوَاتٍ طِبَاقًا ۖ مَا تَرَىٰ فِي خَلْقِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ مِنْ تَفَاوُتٍ ۖ فَارْجِعِ الْبَصَرَ هَلْ تَرَىٰ مِنْ فُطُورٍ \n\nAllathee khalaqa sabAAa samawatin tibaqan ma tara fee khalqi alrrahmani min tafawutin fairjiAAi albasara hal tara min futoorin\n\nThe One Who created the seven heavens, one above another, you will not see any flaw in the creation of the Compassionate. Look once again, do you see any flaw?(3)\n\nثُمَّ ارْجِعِ الْبَصَرَ كَرَّتَيْنِ يَنْقَلِبْ إِلَيْكَ الْبَصَرُ خَاسِئًا وَهُوَ حَسِيرٌ \n\nThumma irjiAAi albasara karratayni yanqalib ilayka albasaru khasian wahuwa haseerun\n\nThen look still another time, yet again your sight will come back bewildered, and feel exhausted.(4)\n\nوَلَقَدْ زَيَّنَّا السَّمَاءَ الدُّنْيَا بِمَصَابِيحَ وَجَعَلْنَاهَا رُجُومًا لِلشَّيَاطِينِ ۖ وَأَعْتَدْنَا لَهُمْ عَذَابَ السَّعِيرِ \n\nWalaqad zayyanna alssamaa alddunya bimasabeeha wajaAAalnaha rujooman lilshshayateeni waaAAtadna lahum AAathaba alssaAAeeri\n\nWe have decorated the heaven of this world with lamps and We made them as missiles for pelting the shaitans and thus prepared for them the scourge of flames.(5)\n\nوَلِلَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا بِرَبِّهِمْ عَذَابُ جَهَنَّمَ ۖ وَبِئْسَ الْمَصِيرُ \n\nWalillatheena kafaroo birabbihim AAathabu jahannama wabisa almaseeru\n\nAs for those who disbelieve their Rabb, there will be the punishment of hell, which is an evil abode.(6)\n\nإِذَا أُلْقُوا فِيهَا سَمِعُوا لَهَا شَهِيقًا وَهِيَ تَفُورُ \n\nItha olqoo feeha samiAAoo laha shaheeqan wahiya tafooru\n\nWhen they will be plunged into its fire, they shall hear its roaring and boiling(7)\n\nتَكَادُ تَمَيَّزُ مِنَ الْغَيْظِ ۖ كُلَّمَا أُلْقِيَ فِيهَا فَوْجٌ سَأَلَهُمْ خَزَنَتُهَا أَلَمْ يَأْتِكُمْ نَذِيرٌ \n\nTakadu tamayyazu mina alghaythi kullama olqiya feeha fawjun saalahum khazanatuha alam yatikum natheerun\n\nas though bursting with rage. Every time a group is plunged therein, its guards will ask: "Did not a Warner come to you?"(8)\n\nقَالُوا بَلَىٰ قَدْ جَاءَنَا نَذِيرٌ فَكَذَّبْنَا وَقُلْنَا مَا نَزَّلَ اللَّهُ مِنْ شَيْءٍ إِنْ أَنْتُمْ إِلَّا فِي ضَلَالٍ كَبِيرٍ \n\nQaloo bala qad jaana natheerun fakaththabna waqulna ma nazzala Allahu min shayin in antum illa fee dalalin kabeerin\n\nThey will answer: "Yes indeed, a Warner did come to us, but we rejected him and said, Allah has revealed nothing - you are merely in gross error."(9)\n\nوَقَالُوا لَوْ كُنَّا نَسْمَعُ أَوْ نَعْقِلُ مَا كُنَّا فِي أَصْحَابِ السَّعِيرِ \n\nWaqaloo law kunna nasmaAAu aw naAAqilu ma kunna fee ashabi alssaAAeeri\n\nThey will further say: "Had we only listened or used our intelligence, we would have not been among the inmates of the blazing fire."(10)\n\nفَاعْتَرَفُوا بِذَنْبِهِمْ فَسُحْقًا لِأَصْحَابِ السَّعِيرِ \n\nFaiAAtarafoo bithanbihim fasuhqan liashabi alssaAAeeri\n\nThus shall they confess their sin; so away from the mercy of Allah will be the dwellers of hell.(11)\n\nإِنَّ الَّذِينَ يَخْشَوْنَ رَبَّهُمْ بِالْغَيْبِ لَهُمْ مَغْفِرَةٌ وَأَجْرٌ كَبِيرٌ \n\nInna allatheena yakhshawna rabbahum bialghaybi lahum maghfiratun waajrun kabeerun\n\nAs for those who fear their Rabb, although they have not seen Him, shall have forgiveness and a great reward.(12)\n\nوَأَسِرُّوا قَوْلَكُمْ أَوِ اجْهَرُوا بِهِ ۖ إِنَّهُ عَلِيمٌ بِذَاتِ الصُّدُورِ \n\nWaasirroo qawlakum awi ijharoo bihi innahu AAaleemun bithati alssudoori\n\nWhether you speak in secret or aloud, surely He is aware of all that is in the breasts.(13)\n\nأَلَا يَعْلَمُ مَنْ خَلَقَ وَهُوَ اللَّطِيفُ الْخَبِيرُ \n\nAla yaAAlamu man khalaqa wahuwa allateefu alkhabeeru\n\nWould He not know, Who has created them? He is the Knower of finest mysteries, and aware of everything.(14)\n\nهُوَ الَّذِي جَعَلَ لَكُمُ الْأَرْضَ ذَلُولًا فَامْشُوا فِي مَنَاكِبِهَا وَكُلُوا مِنْ رِزْقِهِ ۖ وَإِلَيْهِ النُّشُورُ \n\nHuwa allathee jaAAala lakumu alarda thaloolan faimshoo fee manakibiha wakuloo min rizqihi wailayhi alnnushooru\n\nIt is He Who has made the earth subservient to you, to walk through its tracts and eat of His provided sustenance. To Him is the return at resurrection.(15)\n\nأَأَمِنْتُمْ مَنْ فِي السَّمَاءِ أَنْ يَخْسِفَ بِكُمُ الْأَرْضَ فَإِذَا هِيَ تَمُورُ \n\nAamintum man fee alssamai an yakhsifa bikumu alarda faitha hiya tamooru\n\nDo you feel secure that He Who is in heaven, will not cause the earth to cave in beneath you and start shaking suddenly?(16)\n\nأَمْ أَمِنْتُمْ مَنْ فِي السَّمَاءِ أَنْ يُرْسِلَ عَلَيْكُمْ حَاصِبًا ۖ فَسَتَعْلَمُونَ كَيْفَ نَذِيرِ \n\nAm amintum man fee alssamai an yursila AAalaykum hasiban fasataAAlamoona kayfa natheeri\n\nOr do you feel secure that He Who is in heaven will not send against you a violent tornado, then you shall know how was My warning!(17)\n\nوَلَقَدْ كَذَّبَ الَّذِينَ مِنْ قَبْلِهِمْ فَكَيْفَ كَانَ نَكِيرِ \n\nWalaqad kaththaba allatheena min qablihim fakayfa kana nakeeri\n\nThose who have gone before them likewise disbelieved, then see how terrible was the way I rejected them?(18)\n\nأَوَلَمْ يَرَوْا إِلَى الطَّيْرِ فَوْقَهُمْ صَافَّاتٍ وَيَقْبِضْنَ ۚ مَا يُمْسِكُهُنَّ إِلَّا الرَّحْمَٰنُ ۚ إِنَّهُ بِكُلِّ شَيْءٍ بَصِيرٌ \n\nAwalam yaraw ila alttayri fawqahum saffatin wayaqbidna ma yumsikuhunna illa alrrahmanu innahu bikulli shayin baseerun\n\nDo they not observe the birds above them spreading their wings and folding them? None could hold them except the Compassionate (Allah), surely it is He Who watches over all things.(19)\n\nأَمَّنْ هَٰذَا الَّذِي هُوَ جُنْدٌ لَكُمْ يَنْصُرُكُمْ مِنْ دُونِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ ۚ إِنِ الْكَافِرُونَ إِلَّا فِي غُرُورٍ \n\nAmman hatha allathee huwa jundun lakum yansurukum min dooni alrrahmani ini alkafiroona illa fee ghuroorin\n\nWhat force is there that can help you besides the Compassionate? In fact, the unbelievers are suffering from delusion.(20)\n\nأَمَّنْ هَٰذَا الَّذِي يَرْزُقُكُمْ إِنْ أَمْسَكَ رِزْقَهُ ۚ بَلْ لَجُّوا فِي عُتُوٍّ وَنُفُورٍ \n\nAmman hatha allathee yarzuqukum in amsaka rizqahu bal lajjoo fee AAutuwwin wanufoorin\n\nOr who is there that can provide you if He withholds His provision? Yet, they persist in rebellion and aversion from the truth.(21)\n\nأَفَمَنْ يَمْشِي مُكِبًّا عَلَىٰ وَجْهِهِ أَهْدَىٰ أَمَّنْ يَمْشِي سَوِيًّا عَلَىٰ صِرَاطٍ مُسْتَقِيمٍ \n\nAfaman yamshee mukibban AAala wajhihi ahda amman yamshee sawiyyan AAala siratin mustaqeemin\n\nJust think, who is rightly guided: he who walks with his face bent down, or he who walks properly on an even path?(22)\n\nقُلْ هُوَ الَّذِي أَنْشَأَكُمْ وَجَعَلَ لَكُمُ السَّمْعَ وَالْأَبْصَارَ وَالْأَفْئِدَةَ ۖ قَلِيلًا مَا تَشْكُرُونَ \n\nQul huwa allathee anshaakum wajaAAala lakumu alssamAAa waalabsara waalafidata qaleelan ma tashkuroona\n\nSay: "It is He Who has brought you into being, gave you the faculties of hearing, seeing, feeling and understanding: yet you are seldom thankful."(23)\n\nقُلْ هُوَ الَّذِي ذَرَأَكُمْ فِي الْأَرْضِ وَإِلَيْهِ تُحْشَرُونَ \n\nQul huwa allathee tharaakum fee alardi wailayhi tuhsharoona\n\nSay: "It is He Who has multiplied you in the earth, and before Him you shall all be assembled."(24)\n\nوَيَقُولُونَ مَتَىٰ هَٰذَا الْوَعْدُ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ صَادِقِينَ \n\nWayaqooloona mata hatha alwaAAdu in kuntum sadiqeena\n\nThey ask: "When will this promise be fulfilled, if what you say is true?"(25)\n\nقُلْ إِنَّمَا الْعِلْمُ عِنْدَ اللَّهِ وَإِنَّمَا أَنَا نَذِيرٌ مُبِينٌ \n\nQul innama alAAilmu AAinda Allahi wainnama ana natheerun mubeenun\n\nTell them: "Allah Alone has the knowledge of that; my mission is only to warn you plainly."(26)\n\nفَلَمَّا رَأَوْهُ زُلْفَةً سِيئَتْ وُجُوهُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا وَقِيلَ هَٰذَا الَّذِي كُنْتُمْ بِهِ تَدَّعُونَ \n\nFalamma raawhu zulfatan seeat wujoohu allatheena kafaroo waqeela hatha allathee kuntum bihi taddaAAoona\n\nBut, when they shall see it close at hand, the faces of the disbelievers will turn black with gloom, and it will be said to them: "This is which you were calling for."(27)\n\nقُلْ أَرَأَيْتُمْ إِنْ أَهْلَكَنِيَ اللَّهُ وَمَنْ مَعِيَ أَوْ رَحِمَنَا فَمَنْ يُجِيرُ الْكَافِرِينَ مِنْ عَذَابٍ أَلِيمٍ \n\nQul araaytum in ahlakaniya Allahu waman maAAiya aw rahimana faman yujeeru alkafireena min AAathabin aleemin\n\nFurther say: "Have you ever considered that even if Allah destroys me as well as those with me or bestows His mercy on us; who will save the disbelievers from a painful punishment?"(28)\n\nقُلْ هُوَ الرَّحْمَٰنُ آمَنَّا بِهِ وَعَلَيْهِ تَوَكَّلْنَا ۖ فَسَتَعْلَمُونَ مَنْ هُوَ فِي ضَلَالٍ مُبِينٍ \n\nQul huwa alrrahmanu amanna bihi waAAalayhi tawakkalna fasataAAlamoona man huwa fee dalalin mubeenin\n\nSay: "He is the Compassionate: in Him we have believed, and in Him we have put our trust. Soon you will find out, which one of us is in the manifest error."(29)\n\nقُلْ أَرَأَيْتُمْ إِنْ أَصْبَحَ مَاؤُكُمْ غَوْرًا فَمَنْ يَأْتِيكُمْ بِمَاءٍ مَعِينٍ \n\nQul araaytum in asbaha maokum ghawran faman yateekum bimain maAAeenin\n\nSay: "Have you ever considered that if all the water you have, sink down in the ground, who is it, that will bring you the clear-flowing water?"(30)</string>
    <string name="surat_alkahf">Surat Al-Kahf</string>
    <string name="surat_almulk">Surat Al-Mulk</string>
    <string name="choosesura">Choose a Chapter From Quran</string>

    <string name="pref_tab1">Reminders Setting</string>
    <string name="pref_tab2">Athan Settings</string>
    <string name="pref_tab0">General Settings</string>
    <string name="calc_method">Calculation Method</string>
    <string name="calc_method_karachi">University of Islamic Sciences, Karachi</string>
    <string name="calc_method_isna">Islamic Society of North America</string>
    <string name="calc_method_mwl">Muslim World League</string>
    <string name="calc_method_mekkah">Umm al-Qura, Makkah</string>
    <string name="calc_method_egypt">Egyptian General Authority of Survey</string>
    <string name="calc_method_jafri">Jafri</string>
    <string name="calc_method_iran">Institute of Geophysics, University of Tehran</string>
    <string name="calc_method_oman">Ministry of Endowments and religious affairs, Oman</string>
    <string name="asr_calc_method">Asr Time Calculation Method</string>
    <string name="asr_calc_method_standard">Shafi, Malki, Hanbli</string>
    <string name="asr_calc_method_hanafi">Hanafi</string>

    <string name="fajr_reminder_type">Fajr Reminder Type</string>
    <string name="duhr_reminder_type">Duhr Reminder Type</string>
    <string name="asr_reminder_type">Asr Reminder Type</string>
    <string name="maghrib_reminder_type">Maghrib Reminder Type</string>
    <string name="isha_reminder_type">Isha Reminder Type</string>

    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_viberate">Vibrate</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_ring">Phone Ring</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_1">Athan 1</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_2">Athan 2</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_3">Athan 3</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_4">Athan 4</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_5">Athan 5</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_6">Athan 6</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_7">Athan 7</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_8">Athan 8</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_9">Athan 9</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_10">Athan 10</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_athan_11">Athan 11</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_takbeer_1">Takbeer 1</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_takbeer_2">Takbeer 2</string>
    <string name="prayer_reminder_type_takbeer_3">Takbeer 3</string>



    <string name="high_latitude_adjustment">High Latitude Adjustment Method</string>

    <string name="highlatitudeadjustment_none">None</string>
    <string name="highlatitudeadjustment_midnight">Midnight Rule</string>
    <string name="highlatitudeadjustment_seventh">One Seventh Rule</string>
    <string name="highlatitudeadjustment_anglebased">Angle Based Rule</string>
    <string name="calcs_method">calculation method</string>

    <string name="athan_type">Type Of Reminder For Prayer Time</string>
    <string name="record_audio">Record The Audio For This Supplication</string>
    <string name="ok">ok</string>
    <string name="location_services_not_enabled">Location services is required in order to calculate prayer times correctly. Do you want to enable location services now?</string>

    <string name="latitude_adjustment_method_chosen">You live in a high latitude location. Isha and Fajr times were adjusted based on angle</string>
    <string name="choose_audio_file">Choose Audio File</string>

    <string name="mulkThikrSettings">Surat Al-Mulk Reminders Settings</string> 
    <string name="remindMemulk">Remind Me Of Surat Al-Mulk</string> 
    <string name="mulk_reminder_type">Reminder Method</string>
    <string name="stop_recording">Stop Recording</string>
    <string name="thikr_text_required">Supplication text is required. Please add text.</string>
    <string name="recording">Recording</string>
    <string name="next">Next</string>
    <string name="remove_ads">Remove Ads</string>
    <string name="time_adjustment">Adjust Prayer Times</string>





    <string name="pref_category_font">Fonts</string>

    <string name="pref_font_arabic_size">pref_font_arabic_size</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_size_title">Arabic Font Size</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_size_summary">Font size of Arabic in dua\'</string>
    <integer name="pref_font_arabic_size_default">24</integer>
    <integer name="pref_font_arabic_size_max">30</integer>
    <integer name="pref_font_arabic_size_min">20</integer>

    <string name="pref_font_arabic_typeface">pref_font_arabic_typeface</string>
    <string name="pref_font_directory">fonts_2</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_typeface_title">Arabic Font</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_typeface_summary">Font used for Arabic dua\'</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_typeface_default">fonts_2/UthmanTN1 Ver09.otf</string>
    <string name="pref_font_arabic_typeface_preview">بِسْمِ اللهِ</string>

    <string name="pref_font_other_size">pref_font_other_size</string>
    <string name="pref_font_other_size_title">Translation and Reference Font Size</string>
    <string name="pref_font_other_size_summary">Font size of translations and references</string>
    <integer name="pref_font_other_size_default">14</integer>
    <integer name="pref_font_other_size_max">24</integer>
    <integer name="pref_font_other_size_min">12</integer>

    <string name="hisn_almuslim">Hisnul Muslim</string>

    <string name="app_name_about">Hisnul Muslim App</string>
    <string name="version_name">Version 0.1.1</string>
    <string name="beta_version">0.06 - RecyclerView</string>

    <string name="duaDetailFragment">Dua Detail Fragment</string>

    <string name="title_activity_dua_detail">DuaDetail</string>

    <string name="hello_world">Hello world!</string>

    <string name="about_us">
        <![CDATA[
            Hisnul Muslim is a collection of supplications for various occasions compiled by Dr. Sa\'eed bin Ali bin Wahaf Al-Qahtani. The author is from amongst the senior students of the former Grand Mufti of Saudi Arabia, Shaykh Abdul Aziz bin Abdullah bin Baz (May Allah have mercy on him).
            <br/><br/>
            <big><b>Contributors</b></big><br/>
            Ahmed El-Helw (<a href="http://twitter.com/ahmedre">@ahmedre</a>)<br/>
            Azhar Ali (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pub/md-azhar-ali/90/251/140">LinkedIn</a>)<br/>
            Abdul Majed Ahmed (<a href="https://twitter.com/AbdulMajed19">@AbdulMajed19</a>)<br/>
            Hussaini Zulkifli (<a href="https://twitter.com/HussainiZul">@HussainiZul</a>)<br/>
            Mohammad Khalid Hussain (<a href="https://www.github.com/khalid.hussain">GitHub</a>)
            <br/><br/>

            <big><b>OpenSource Projects</b></big><br/>
            AutoFitTextView (<a href="https://github.com/grantland/android-autofittextview">GitHub</a>)<br/>
            VNTNumberPicker Preference (<a href="https://github.com/vanniktech/VNTNumberPickerPreference"/>GitHub</a>)<br/>
            VNTFontList Preference (<a href="https://github.com/vanniktech/VNTFontListPreference"/>GitHub</a>)
            <br/><br/>

            <big><b>Special Thanks</b></big><br/>
            Ahmad Sabree (<a href="https://twitter.com/sabree01">@sabree01</a>)<br/>
        ]]>
    </string>

    <string name="bookmarks_none">You have no bookmarks yet.</string>
    <string name="action_share_title">Share Dua</string>
    <string name="action_share_credit">via @HisnulMuslimApp</string>

    <string name="button_share_icon"></string>
    <string name="button_fav_icon">{faw-star}</string>
    <string name="button_fav_icon_no">{faw-star-o}</string>
    <string name="snackbar_text_begin">Removed Dua #</string>
    <string name="snackbar_text_end">" from bookmarks"</string>
    <string name="snackbar_action">undo</string>
    <string name="gradual_volume">Increase volume gradually</string>

</resources>
